<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glorie of man consisting in the excellencie and perfection of woman Gathered out of Holie Scriptures, and most renowned wryters; as well ancient, as moderne; ecclesiaticall, as morall. Wherevnto is annexed The duetie of husbands.</title>
            <author>Raban, Edward, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1286:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glorie of man consisting in the excellencie and perfection of woman Gathered out of Holie Scriptures, and most renowned wryters; as well ancient, as moderne; ecclesiaticall, as morall. Wherevnto is annexed The duetie of husbands.</title>
                  <author>Raban, Edward, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 911 [i.e. 119], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the author [Edward Raban],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>June 6, 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The duetie of husbands: drawne out of Master Carter his boke of Christian commonwealth" has separate half title; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf has a woodcut of a rooster.</note>
                  <note>Page 119 misnumbered 911.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a large cock struts by smaller birds that are pecking at the ground</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>THE</hi> GLORIE <hi>OF MAN Conſisting in</hi> The Excellencie and perfection of Woman, Gathered out of Holie SCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVRES, and moſt Renowned <hi>Wryters; as well Ancient, as Moderne; Eccleſiasticall, as Morall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherevnto is annexed <hi>The duetie of Huſbands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ABERDENE, Printed by the Author, <hi>June</hi> 6, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Jlluſtrious LADIE, ANNA CAMBEL; LADIE MARQVES of HVNTLEY, COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESSE of AENZIE, BADINACH, LOCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ABRE, STRADOWN, AND STRABOGIE; LADIE GORDON
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my ſelf, from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Sarcaſtick, bitter, too looſe, &amp; liberall ſpeaches, agaynſt the moſt Noble, Worthie, and Tranſcendant Sexe of WOMEN, (which ſome, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing their own imperfect weakneſſe, may apprehend to be
<hi>Calumnies,</hi> and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue to the whole Sexe) I here make humble Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb facs="tcp:14376:3"/> &amp;, with all Reverence, preſent vnto your Ladiſhips Honorable Hands, this litle TREATISE; as a part of my Studie, in my weariſome Journie, this halfe yeare by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, in forraygne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys.</p>
            <p>Which, indeed, MADAME, I aimed for Your La: the laſt New-years-day; if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of weather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie winds, had not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>But, through the mercie of GOD, your La: Servant being ſafelie arrived, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no more, but that this <hi>Abortiue</hi> may ſhelter it ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:14376:3"/> vnder the ſhadow of Your La: Honourable Affection. Then may I think my ſelfe happie, and the payns well beſtowed.</p>
            <p>Not doubting, but that it ſhall ſo plead for me, that by a juſt judgement of all Your La: moſt Glorious, Noble, and Gracious Sexe, I ſhall be pronounced guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, quyte, and free, from all Aſperſion, and Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnjuſtlie here to fore layd to my charge.</p>
            <p>How-ſo-ever, Madame, if eyther this <hi>Subject</hi> maye anie wayes ſeeme pleaſing vnto Your La: or my ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:14376:4"/> ſerviceable; all my cited <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> never thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues halfe ſo GRACED; as I will continuallie confeſſe MY FORTVNES HONOVRED.</p>
            <p>And, thus, MOST NOBLE, AND GRACIOVS LADIE,</p>
            <l>
               <hi>With humble Heart, true mynd, and tempred Brayne,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>NED <hi>vowes, Your Sexe poore</hi> PRINTER <hi>to remayne.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:4"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Men are ſo vncharitable, ſayth Master <hi>Feltham,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>RESOL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pag.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 100.</note> as to thinke <hi>All Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bad:</hi> and others ſo credulous, as they belieue, <hi>They are all good.</hi> But, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, although everie man ſpeaketh, as hee findeth; yet there is <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to direct our
<hi>Opinion,</hi> without experience of the whole Sexe: Which, in a ſtrict Examination, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more for <hi>The Honour of Women,</hi> than most men, as yet, haue acknowledged.</p>
            <p>At the first, She was created his Equall. Onelie the difference was in the Sexe. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>GEN.</hi> 5.</note> they both were Man.</p>
            <p>If anie will argue from the Text, That Male and Female made Man; ſo the Man being put firſt, was therefore the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt: I anſwere; So the Euening and the Morning were the firſt day, ſayth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: putting ever the Night before the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>GEN.</hi> 1</note>

               <pb facs="tcp:14376:5"/> Day: otherwyſe the Day was vnperfect.</p>
            <p>And, altho <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> abſurdlie, wold ſeeme to affirme, That, before the Fall, Man had Prioritie: Yet Saynct <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> ſtronglie, and truelie, confuteth his Groſſe Opinion.</p>
            <p>Now, all muſt grant, Her Bodie to bee more Amiable, Admirable, and Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, than Mans. She is fuller of Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and Noble Natures Wonders: both for Conception, and foſtering the producted Birth.</p>
            <p>And, who, then, dare thinke, that GOD would put a worſer Soule, into a better Bodie?</p>
            <p>It is certayne, that Women are of colder Conſtitution, than boyling Man: and, ſo, more temperate.</p>
            <p>Heate it ſelfe tranſporteth Man to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderation, and Furie: and hurrieth him to a Savage, and Libidinous Violence. But Women are, naturallie, more modeſt. And Modeſtie is, indeede, the verie Seat, and Dwelling-place, of Vertue: And
<q>
                  <l>Fond Fortunes blaſts cannot prevayle,</l>
                  <l>To over-throw Dame Vertues Sayle.</l> 
               </q> 
            </p>
            <p>Whence, I pray you, proceede the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:14376:5"/> abhorride Villanies, but from a Maſculine vnbluſhing Impudence? And what a deale of Sweetneſſe doe wee finde in a mylde Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition? For
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Rage runnes ſwiftlie, ſtep aſide, and ſee,</l>
                     <l>How hard th' Approaches of fearce Furie bee.</l>
                  </lg> 
               </q> 
            </p>
            <p>If a Woman groweth bolde, and daring, wee diſlyke her, and ſay, <hi>Shee is too lyke a Man.</hi> And yet, in our ſelues, wee magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, what in her wee condemne. Is not this great injuſtice?</p>
            <p>Everie Man is ſo much the better, by how much the nearer hee commeth vnto GOD. And in nothing can Man bee more lyke vnto GOD, than in beeing Mercifull. Yet Woman exceedeth Man verie farre, in Mercie, Pittie, Pietie, Chartie, and Rueth.</p>
            <p>And, whereas wee are ſtill exhorted to loue, I am aſſured, that Women are everie where ſpoken of, for tranſcending in that Qualitie.</p>
            <p>Men, indeede, haue ever holden Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; beene Judges in their owne cauſes: inacting their owne Wills, and not bearing the Women ſpeake: whereby, verie eaſilie,
<pb facs="tcp:14376:6"/> they may bee concluded guiltie. But let Men know, that
<q>
                  <l>Who judgement giues, and will but one ſide heare,</l>
                  <l>(Though hee judge right) is no good Iuſticiere.</l> 
               </q> 
            </p>
            <p>How-ſo-ever, for my part, I would gladlie honour Vertue in everie Sexe. And, I thinke, in the Generall, I ſhall finde it more in Women, than in Men; though weaker, and more infirmlie guarded.</p>
            <p>And, though Women bee the Better, yet may they bee wrought (by wicked Men) to bee the worſer.</p>
            <p>Neyther ſhall the faults of manie, make mee vncharitable to all: nor the Goodneſſe of ſome, make mee credulous of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Yet, hitherto, I confeſſe, I haue found more ſweete, and conſtant, Goodneſſe, in Women, than in Men: for, of ſuch men as are conſtant in true Goodneſſe, I haue found no great Number.</p>
            <p>And thus I end my Prologue, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth not with Apologies; neyther doe I end it with any intreatie of a kinde cenſure, which might ſeeme to diſparage this Work, and beg partialitie. But if in theſe weake
<pb facs="tcp:14376:6"/> Extractions, the Judicious and Godlie Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, may bee anie wayes pleaſed in their increaſing affections ſtill towardes Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Vertue, (all by-Reſpects put away) my Petitions ſhall ever bee to the GOD of all Goodneſſe, to perpetuate their Happineſſe; I ever remayning</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Their ImmutablE HonoureR.
<figure>
                     <q>HAUD INFERIORA SEQUTUS.</q>
                     <figDesc>sun shining on a plant</figDesc>
                  </figure> 
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:7"/>
            <head>The Authors, from whom this little Treatiſe hath its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall; Beſide the Holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Chronicles of all Nations, and in all Languages.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 AMmianus Marcellius.</item>
               <item>2 Ariſtotle.</item>
               <item>3 Aulus Gellius.</item>
               <item>4 Boccace.</item>
               <item>5 Bohem.</item>
               <item>6 Carter.</item>
               <item>7 Cato.</item>
               <item>8 Cicero,</item>
               <item>9 Chryſoſtome.</item>
               <item>10 Curtius Solinus.</item>
               <item>11 Diodorus Siculus.</item>
               <item>12 Epigenes.</item>
               <item>13 Eraſmus.</item>
               <item>14 Euſebius.</item>
               <item>15 Feltham.</item>
               <item>16 Giero.</item>
               <item>17 Gorgias Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</item>
               <item>18 Grantzio.</item>
               <item>19 Gybſon.</item>
               <item>20 Herodote.</item>
               <item>21 Hieronymus.</item>
               <item>22 Hortantius.</item>
               <item>23 Iohan Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conville.</item>
               <item>24 Iuſtinus.</item>
               <item>25 Lactantius.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14376:7"/> 26 Marcus Varro</item>
               <item>27 Mercurius Triſmegiſtus.</item>
               <item>28 Munſterus.</item>
               <item>29 Origen.</item>
               <item>30 Oroſius.</item>
               <item>31 Ovid.</item>
               <item>32 Petrus Cirni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</item>
               <item>33 Periander.</item>
               <item>34 Pindar.</item>
               <item>35 Plato.</item>
               <item>36 Plinius.</item>
               <item>37 Plutarch.</item>
               <item>38 Pompeïus.</item>
               <item>39 Pomponius Mela.</item>
               <item>40 Pythagoras.</item>
               <item>41 Siculus.</item>
               <item>42 Scotus Subti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</item>
               <item>43 Socrates.</item>
               <item>44 Solinus.</item>
               <item>45 Steſichoris.</item>
               <item>46 Symphrorian Champer.</item>
               <item>47 Taylor.</item>
               <item>48 Theophraſtus.</item>
               <item>49 Thevet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonozin.</item>
               <item>50 Thomaſius.</item>
               <item>51 Trogus.</item>
               <item>52 Virgil.</item>
               <item>53 Xenocrates.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>And others.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:14376:8"/>
            <head>To the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN repreſenting to the whole Worldes view,</l>
               <l>The lyuelie Pourtrait of the Worldes Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd:</l>
               <l>Yea, Natures Darling, with Her Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes due:</l>
               <l>With louelie Grace, and Merits Rayes attir'd:</l>
               <l>The Worth and Vertue of that Sacred Frame,</l>
               <l>Thy humble Service doeth thy Preſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</l>
               <l>To vindicate, and blaze abroade Her Fame.</l>
               <l>Each one must ſay, Thou hast deſerved well.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. I. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div n="women's excellence" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14376:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>The glory of Man, <hi>Conſisting in</hi> The Excellencie and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of WOMAN.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>Of the Creation of</hi> WOMAN, <hi>and Her Perfection.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owbeit THVCY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIDES, <note place="margin">THVCY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIDES.</note> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, (out of an heath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke humour) was of opinion; That as the Women ought to bee good Houſe-keepers, and ſeldome ſeene abroad; neyther ſhould their good Name, Fame, nor Beautie, goe farder than the threſhold of their doores: Yet worthie <hi>Plutarch,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">PLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARCH.</note> (a Man farre more excellent in Wit &amp; Learning) treating of the Excellencie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14376:9"/> of renowned Women, agreeth with the learned <hi>Gorgias Leontanus,</hi> and
<note place="margin">Gorgias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eontanus</note> ſayeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That not onlie Her Beautie, but alſo Her rare Vertues, good Behavior, comelie Manners, and other angelicall Perfections, ſhould no wayes be ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered: But, in the Orations of learned men, made knowne; even to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cowragement of Poſteritie; according to the Lawes of the ancient <hi>Romanes;</hi> who held it for great impietie, only to make the groſſeſt halfe of Mankynde renowned, and let the more excellent deeds, of the Nobler ſort, bee buried in oblivion.</p>
                     <p>And, therefore, according to my ſlender Skill, and abilitie, I vow to doe my beſt herein: though I preſume nor to bee called abſolutelie the Author hereof; but by way of gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and truelie tranſlating, of learned mens juſt Tryalls, and ſound Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, in the prayſe of ſo rare, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, comelie, wyſe, louelie, perfect, amiable, and precious a Creature, as is WOMAN, the Crowne, and Glorie, of MAN, even the Mother of all living Soules.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14376:9"/> Neyther will I ſpeake onlie of late tymes, ſince the dayes of
<hi>Annacus,</hi> or <note place="margin">Annac. Deucals</note> 
                        <hi>Deucalion;</hi> but even fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning, and firſt creation of WOMAN: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Her ſplendant Brightneſſe maye ſhyne the clearer, dazeling the duſtie deeds of ſlalow-witted <hi>Man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>NOw, it is ſayd in the firſt and ſecond Chapters of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> That the LORD created the firſt man <hi>[Adam]</hi> even of the duſt and ſlyme of the earth, breathing into his noſtrils the breath of lyfe: and ſo he became a living ſoule; being innocent, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctlie holie, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the Image of GOD.</p>
                     <p>Then, marke, That <hi>Man</hi> was made of a dead lumpe, and of the worſt of the earth. And, when GOD had put His owne Spirit therein, and made it a comelie, fayre, yea, holie, and divine Creature; then, out of the ſame purified ſubſtance, Hee made a more excellent Angelicall Creature; even EVAH, the <hi>Woman,</hi> and Mother of vs all.</p>
                     <p>Here might juſtlie be ſhowne innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14376:10"/> Teſtimonies, for the Honour and Prayſe of Women, from the verie creation, vntill this day: 1. That everie worke of GOD exceedeth, excelleth, and out-reacheth each other, in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and goodneſſe; and ſtill the laſt, for to bee beſt. 2. That <hi>Man</hi> was the cauſe of the Womans fall; by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting her companie. 3. That the <hi>Woman</hi> made denyall, to eate of the forbidden Fruit; and was overcome, by great and ſubtile temptations: and, that Man, verie impudentlie, and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyſedlie, without anie gayn-ſaying, at the firſt offer, tooke, and ate; and ſo verie raſhlie brake the LORD'S Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. 4. That whereas the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſayeth, that Wyues ſhould bee ſubject to their Husbands; is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That therfore, the Men are better than Women: but in reſpect of Her Fall. 5. That the fall of
<hi>Evah,</hi> was greatlie to the manifeſtation of the Glorie and Power of GOD: yea, and a moſt happie Fall, to the Elected peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the LORD.</p>
                     <p>Theſe, I ſay, with thouſandes moe, might heere, truelie, and playnlie, bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14376:10"/> proven: but I omit the reſt, vntill my ſecond worke of this qualitie: which, (if this bee jangled agaynſt) ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie compeare, even to the vtter ſhame of all the Fame-ſtayners of Women. And thus I proceede in Their due and juſt Prayſe.</p>
                     <p>Now, it is ſayd, <hi>(Geneſ.</hi> 3.) that <hi>the ſeed of the Woman, ſhould bruize the head</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">GENE SIS 3.</note> 
                        <hi>of the Serpent.</hi> And by this <hi>Seed,</hi> is meant our gracious Redeemer, IESUS, our Saviour: Bleſſed for ever: Amen.</p>
                     <p>And, who ſo would rightlie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what <hi>Woman</hi> is vnto <hi>Man;</hi> Shee is, in verie deed, the firſt &amp; chiefe eſſentiall Good, and Perfect Benefit of GOD, vnto
<hi>Man.</hi> For, without that goodlie Creature, Man had never bene perfected: but in more miſerable ſtate, on earth, than anie beaſt: for each of them had his Maike, for his ſolace, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and procreation.</p>
                     <p>Thus, to conclude our firſt Chapter, let none denye, But that Woman is Man's Equall (and more) in every good poynt; and formoſt part-taker of every Heavenlie Gift and Grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aboue: Being, as ſayd is, compoſed both of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14376:11"/> more excellent Subſtance, and Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And, in Her, as in a rare, ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, coſtlie, and precious Boothe, or Shop, (and from Her) doe ſhyne the beams of Beautie, Comelinehe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, Vertue, Prudencie, Pietie, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and practiſe in good manners: Farre exceeding groſſe Man: except, indeed, in ſtrength, wherein he excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Woman mightilie, to commit all manner of Crueltie and Naughtineſſe: and Shee the weaker Veſſell, both in bodie and mynd, to commit anie evill. And, though Man ſeeme to brag of his ſtrength, yet let him know,
<q>
                           <lg>
                              <l>That what Man holdes, hanges but by ſlender Twyne.</l>
                              <l>By ſudden chance the ſtrongest thinges declyne.</l>
                           </lg> 
                        </q> 
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14376:11"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER II. <hi>Of the fayre and goodlie Priviledges, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and given vnto</hi> Women,
<hi>even from the Beginning.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ltho WOMEN had no farder Advantage of Men, than ſayde is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie; to wit, That Shee is made in fayre Paradyſe, and Man there-out: and, Of a good, purified, and liuelie ſubſtance; and hee of a groſſe, heavie, and dead matter: This, I ſaye, might bee ſufficient, to ſtop the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wicked mouthes, of ſuch calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niators, as are not worthie to be called <hi>The Sonnes</hi> (but <hi>The Shame)</hi> of Women. And yet there will remayne a worlde full moe of perfectious Excellencies, and vertuous Qualities, to be found in Women, farre excelling the groſſe, and churliſh conditions of Men. The ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt part whereof, to collect together, and ſet downe in Print, would be a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinthiall, and <hi>Herculean</hi> Travell. Neyther could all the Paper in the worlde contayne Their Worthineſſe;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14376:12"/> nor the worlde contayne the Bookes, which, rightlie, might be written, <hi>In Their just Prayſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And, therefore, I requeſt you, at this tyme, to accept onelie of this my little Knot, drawne out of other mens great Gardens: No more but to ſignifie vnto the worlde, the pretence of my good Will, if poſſiblie my Power could bee amounted to the Spheare of my ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Mynd.</p>
                     <p>Then, for Brevities cauſe, hearken well vnto theſe few (yet notable) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances, of Honourable Women, in tymes paſt; even to the encowrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our gracious Matrons now-a-dayes, yea, and to Succeſſion hereafter: together with a ſtrong Confutation of all graceleſſe Vilependers of this renowned Sexe of Women. Which ſort of men, may fitlie be compared with the worſt ſort of Serpents, or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: which, after generation, having receaved lyfe, in their mothers bellies, gnaw, and eate thorow their mothers ſide, and ſo come foorth: whereby, of neceſſitie, ſhee loſeth her lyfe.</p>
                     <p n="1">Firſtlie, then: There was never ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14376:12"/> a wicked, and vnjuſt Deed, wrought, by all the Women that ever were, as was ſhowne on our Saviour; flat, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctlie contrarie, to the will, counſell, and diſpoſition of Women.</p>
                     <p>Reade, conſideratiuelie, &amp; beholde, how the Women advertiſed, fore-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yea, exhorted the Men, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſslie forbade them, <hi>To lay handes, or</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">MATTH. 26. 19.</note> 
                        <hi>haue adoe, with JESVS:</hi> proclayming and avowing Him,
<hi>To be righteous;</hi> even as the trueth was indeed. Yet, vnhappie men would giue no credence to the Trueth: but, moſt madlie, wickedlie, and impudentlie, even agaynſt all equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, juſtice, and reaſon, they furiouſlie proceeded in their madneſſe: and did not onlie
<hi>Lay handes vpon the Just,</hi> as it were, to hold Him: but, for-ſooth, they bound Him, buffeted Him, mocked Him, ſpitted vpon Him; and, with all the ſpyte the could, they crowned Him even with a Crowne of ſharpe Thorns: Yea, and left not off, till, as ſhamefullie, and with the greateſt ignominie they could invent, <hi>They crucified the LORD of Glorie;</hi> even betwixt two evill-doers, Hee Himſelfe having done no evill at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14376:13"/> all: but was vnjuſtlie accuſed, by ſuch falſe men as themſelues, whome they had ſuborned to be falſe witneſſes.</p>
                     <p>Hearken well, ye Monſters: becauſe your ſex rejected CHRIST, betake you to your brother
<hi>Barabbas;</hi> who beeing guiltie, yee ſaved, and condemned the innocent IESUS; who is the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of WOMEN. For they cryed, <hi>Saue Him, ſaue Him:</hi> but yee cryed, <hi>Crucifie Him, crucifie Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yee prowde, faynt-hearted men<hi>!</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth. chap.</hi> 26.
<hi>verſe</hi> 69. 70 71. 72. 73. 74. <hi>Marke chap</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 66. 67 68. 69. 70.
71. <hi>Luke chap.</hi> 22. <hi>verſe</hi> 56. 57. 58. 59. 60. <hi>Iohn chap.</hi> 18.
<hi>verſe</hi> 17. 18 25. 26. 27.</note> what thinke yee? Was it a fit tyme for His Diſciples to forſake Him in the Garden? And did not His moſte boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Diſciple, <hi>Peter,</hi> denye Him thryſe in ſhort tyme? yea, with curſing, and ſwearing, that he knew Him not.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Innocencie of Women, and Guiltineſſe of Men, in this exceeding great Wickedneſſe, is yet verie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, by theſe folowing Conſequents. Becauſe the men were found too light, and vnworthie, therefore the LORD made choyſe of Women, to be the firſt Proclaymers, and ſounding Trumpets, of His Glorious Reſurrection. The meane tyme His Men-diſciples beeing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14376:13"/> too too forgetfull of what CHRIST had ſayde vnto them manie tymes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, concerning His Reſurrection: yet were they ſaythleſslie forgetfull, and believed not. But, on the contrarie, His Women-Diſciples had great ſayth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred well His words, wayted ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie for His ryſing agayne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from the Graue: when as <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>Marke</hi> 16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.</note> the light-brayned, and ſhalow-witted men, thought all was done, and never to haue heard anie more of their Lord: Diſperſing themſelues, ſome to their former Trade of Fiſhing; others tooke
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. <hi>verſe</hi> 3.</note> their journey into the Countrey, and that vpon the Sabbath Day. Yea, ſome <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Marke chap.</hi> 16.
<hi>verſe</hi> 12. 13</note> of them would not belieue that the LORD was riſen from the dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when it was tolde them of the reſt: no, not when they ſaw the LORD Himſelfe; except they put their handes into His precious wounds: and ſo, if it had bene <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. <hi>verſe</hi> 24. 25. 26. 27.</note> poſſible, to haue holden the LORD ſtill in agonie.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Beholde ſtill the fayre Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Women, by the example of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel, Leah,</hi> and manie others; who were preferred before their husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14376:14"/> had the preeminence to name their children even as pleaſed themſelues: the great Patriarch <hi>Jaakob</hi> himſelfe, father of the twelue Tribes, and many other Worthies, being thereto ſilent.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. How can I worthilie anough ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the prayſe of <hi>Jaill,</hi> the wyfe of
<note place="margin">IAEL.</note> 
                        <hi>Heber</hi> the <hi>Kennite?</hi> who, with her own hands, and alone, ſlue <hi>Siſera,</hi> the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> hoſte: who, in
<note place="margin">IUDGES 4. 18.</note> deede, had made great ſpoyle of the LORD'S People. Beholde, I ſaye That which manie thouſands of men could not atchieue vnto, it pleaſed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> LORD to perfect by a Woman, as an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other worthie
<hi>Pentheſilia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Gracious <hi>Deborah</hi> judged <hi>Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 
                        <note place="margin">DEBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAR.</note> at that tyme: bearing prerogatiue, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> commandement, over all <hi>Iſraell;</hi> as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <note place="margin">IUDGES 5.</note> Captaynes, and Prieſtes, as commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> people. And the LORD bleſſed
<hi>Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> mightilie in her dayes.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Look how farre more excellent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">IUDGES 13. 1. SAM. 25.</note> the Mother of <hi>Sampſon</hi> behaved he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſelfe, both towardes GOD and Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> than did her churliſh husband. And with her, let vs alſo joyne Gracious <hi>Abigaill.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">ABI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAILL.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14376:14"/> 7. See wyſe <hi>Iudeth,</hi> howe cowra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſlie, <note place="margin">IUDETH</note> and valiantlie, ſhe ſlue <hi>Olofer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> and, by that meanes, diſcomfited hundreth thouſandes of the <hi>Aſſyrians:</hi> whyle as the ſillie faynt-hearted men were howling, and lamenting, within the beſiedged Citie of <hi>Bethulia:</hi> not once daring to offer to come foorth: no, not ſo much as once to looke over
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Wall. Sillie Cowards.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Hearken, yet, vnto the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes, of the Royall Priviledges of Women. Looke to the Countrey of <hi>Campaigne;</hi> where that excellent order is yet, from ancient tymes; That if it pleaſe a Gentle-woman to marry with anie meane man, by force of that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage he is inacted a Gentle-man. But if a Gentle-man marrie with a meane woman, it is nothing ſo.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Alſo, worthie <hi>Plutarch</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <note place="margin">PLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARCH.</note> That it is ordayned in <hi>Gallia Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> (to the Honour of Women) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a League, betwixt <hi>Hanniball</hi> &amp; the <hi>Celts;</hi> That, when as a <hi>Celt,</hi> or
<hi>Gall,</hi> ſhould complayne of anie injurie done vnto them by a <hi>Carthagenian,</hi> the lords of <hi>Carthage</hi> were obliedged, to heare
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14376:15"/> the cauſe, and make reſtitution for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wrong. But, on the contrarie, when <hi>Carthagenian</hi> had wronged a <hi>Gall,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Celt,</hi> the
<hi>Celtiſh</hi> women were judge therein, even according to their wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie Diſcretion. Thus were they ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den in high and deſerved Honour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> moſte worthilie preferred before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> men of that Countrey.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. More-over: The <hi>Troglodites</hi> of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> though a barbarous people (as ſayeth <hi>Bohem)</hi> yet, being governed <note place="margin">BOHEM.</note> with Women, as well at home, as abroad in the Warres, are victorious ritch, renowned, and feared of their neyghbouring enemies, who are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned but with the vicious, faynt-hearted, effeminate, cowardlie, and luxurious men.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Here (to the prayſe of women) I cannot omit to rehearſe what one truelie ſpeaketh of the moſte Happie Reygne of our Sacred Soveraygne, <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Queene of
<hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> true Defender of the Fayth, &amp;c. <hi>Bleſſed Queene</hi> ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH (ſayeth hee) <hi>a Princeſſe of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Fame, the Admiration of Her Sexe, the</hi>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14376:15"/> 
                        <hi>Helper of all Nations, the Patterne of Princes, the Delight of Her People, and Terrour of Her Enemies: Borne to weare a temporall crowne on earth, and to bee crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Eternall Glorie in Heaven: Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Iohn Taylor, the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Poët.</note> 
                        <hi>and mayntayned, the true Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie: Repoſed Her onlie Trust in GOD confidentlie: Held the</hi> Ieſuits, <hi>all</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and other</hi> Hyrelinges, <hi>at the Staffs ende ſteadfastlie: Put Her Lawes in Execution reſolutelie, (and yet without all crueltie:) Reygned manie years gloriouſlie: Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this lyfe peaceablie: And liveth in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven triumphantlie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <head>HER EPITAPH.</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Griefes, the Feares, the Terroures, and the Toyles:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The Sleightes, Trickes, Snares, that for Her lyfe were layd:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Popes, Priſons, Poyſons, Pistoles, bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Broyles:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>All theſe incompast Her, poore harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Mayd.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But Shee ſtill trusting in Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Ayd,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Was aye defended, by His Power Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyne.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14376:16"/> 
                              <hi>Her Glorie, and Her Greatneſſe, were diſplayd,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">QUEENE ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH.</note>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>As farre as Sunne and Moone did ever ſhyne.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>GOD'S <hi>mingled Service, Shee did re-refyne,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>From</hi> Romiſh <hi>Rubbiſh, and from Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Droſſe.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shee yearlie made the Pryde of</hi> Spayne <hi>declyne:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>France <hi>and</hi> Belgia, <hi>Shee ſaved from Loſſe.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shee was Artes Patterne, t' Armes Shee was a Patron.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shee liv'd and died a Queene, a Mayd, a Matron.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14376:16"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER III. <hi>Of the Excellencie of</hi> WOMEN, <hi>whom GOD hath made the firſt Mothers of</hi> VERTVE, <hi>and Inſtrumentall Finders<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, of the moſt excellent, and needfull things, in the world.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARCVS VARRO <note place="margin">MARCUS VARRO:</note> teſtifieth, That Women were the firſt Inſtruments, and Finders-out, of the moſt excellent, and needfull things, belonging vnto Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde: to wit;</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Unitie, and Fellowſhip, to dwell together, in Townes, Villages, Freedomes, and Congregations.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That WOMEN were the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venters of LETTERS, and Arte of Writing.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That WOMEN are the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bringers and Ordayners, of Lawes, and Statutes; Politicke, Civill, and Morall.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That the comelie Arte of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, Shearing, or Trimming of mens heads, and beards, firſt begunne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14376:17"/> with Women, in <hi>Sicilia;</hi> and brought from thence, to <hi>Rome,</hi> by
<hi>Tirinius; Rome</hi> having then beene inhabited 554 yeares, without the ſeemlineſſe of this Arte.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That WOMEN are the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venters of Horologies, Dialls, and Clockes; which moſt comfortablie meaſure vnto vs the Day and Night, into 24 parts, Winter and Summer.</p>
                     <p>Then, next vnto GOD, to the glorie of Women bee it ſayde, That no more excellent, and worthie things, than theſe, can bee in the world.</p>
                     <p>What can bee more precious vnto vs, than LETTERS; For, without Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the lyfe of man, yea, and his whole pilgrimage on earth, would bee but a continuall death, and an oblivious buriall. Becauſe nothing can bee done without Letters.</p>
                     <p>Letters are the pillars of everlaſting Memorie.</p>
                     <p>Letters keepe freſh to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance to day, what hath beene done ſo manie thouſand yeares agoe.</p>
                     <p>Letters preſerue all thinges done in our tymes, even vnto our poſterities
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14376:17"/> poſteritie, for ever.</p>
                     <p>Had it not beene for Letters, <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Plato, Ariſtotle, Cato, Theophraſtes, Virgill, Ovid, Cicero,</hi> with the reſt of the goodly fellowſhip of Philoſophers; yea, moſt holie and wyſe Fathers, had not ſo highly beene in eſtimation with the world, nor the world haue reaped ſuch great beneficiall knowledge, as it hath pleaſed GOD, (next vnto His great Mercies) by their paynfull ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, (to our great eaſe) to beſtow vpon vs.</p>
                     <p>But what neede I to ſpeake of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men? and of late tymes? Are not the workes of GOD, even from the beginning, and His miraculous Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet extant amongſt vs? yea, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with His revealed Word and Will; and all by the meanes of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Letters? whereof it pleaſed GOD to make illuſtrious WOMEN the firſt <note place="margin">CAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTA.</note> Author; even Renowned
<hi>Carmenta,</hi> (or, by ſome Writers, named, <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrata)</hi> the mother of
<hi>Evander,</hi> king of <hi>Arcadia.</hi> For whoſe ſake, all men are bound to loue and honour Her Sexe: giving GOD the praiſe, who hath lent vnto
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14376:18"/> Mankinde ſuch an excellent exceeding great Benefite, as are immortall Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                     <p>If anie would heere alleadge, that <note place="margin">PLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIUS.</note> 
                        <hi>Plinius,</hi> with the authoritie of <hi>Epigenes,</hi> would maintayn Letters to haue beene from the beginning of the Creation; yet aboundance of ancient Writers are of the contrarie opinion: amongſt whom is the worthie, &amp; learned <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus:</hi> who thinketh it no ſhame to <note place="margin">THEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STUS-</note> confeſſe, that the Ladie <hi>Leontia,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him, in the face, in diſputation, before an Aſſemblie, and quyte over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw him: and that by reaſon, ſayeth hee, ſhee had the knowledge, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall vſe of Letters: which himſelfe was ignorant of, at that tyme.</p>
                     <p>And Saynct <hi>Hieronymus</hi> confeſſeth <note place="margin">HIERO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NYMUS.</note> the lyke, of a woman, called <hi>Euſtachius:</hi> to the glorie of GOD, in His great Mercies towards Womans Sexe, bee it ſayde.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayeth, that as Man <note place="margin">ARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOTLE</note> commeth of the Woman; even ſo doe all good things, and all excellencie in knowledge of Sciences, Learning, and Vertue, proceede alſo from the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14376:18"/> vnto Man; for his comfort. And therefore, Glorie bee to GOD for Her.</p>
                     <p>To proceede, then, in the juſt praiſe of women. Women haue not onelie beene the firſt inſtrumentall finders of ſuch things as are indeede the Royall Ornaments of Mankynds inward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, (as were Letters afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde:) but alſo manie other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; without the which, man had yet lived, as in former tymes; that is, more lyke brute beaſts, than reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, had it not beene for the wittie helpe, and painfull hand, of vertuous woman. For not onlie from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till <hi>Noah;</hi> but long after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludge, Man lived on Achornes, rootes, barkes of trees, and meale of ſuch lyke thinges. Till, at the laſt, Dame
<hi>Ceres</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">CERES.</note> found out the precious grain of Corne; and, conſequentlie, invented the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and baking of bread, in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of <hi>Greece, Italie,</hi> and <hi>Sicilie.</hi> And therefore was ſhee called a Goddeſſe; yea, and holden for the ſame of all our learned Poëts, even till this day.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, it is ſoothlie ſayde of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14376:19"/> ſame Dame <hi>Ceres,</hi> that ſhee was the firſt ordayner of good Statutes, and maker of Civill Lawes: without the which, no Kingdome, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, Congregation, or Houſholde, could ſtand. And yet all this commeth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelie from GOD, vnto Woman; and GOD maketh her the Deſtributer thereof, vnto man, her other halfe. And for my proofe concerning Dame
<note place="margin">DIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERE. OVID. HERO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DITE. VIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIL.</note> 
                        <hi>Ceres,</hi> I take to witneſſe worthie <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi> in his ſixt Booke; <hi>Ovid,</hi> in his fift Booke of
<hi>Metamorphoſes;</hi> and <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> the father of all Hiſtoricians, in his ſixt Booke. And therefore <hi>Virgil,</hi> in his Booke of <hi>Aeneids,</hi> calleth Her
<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifera;</hi> that is, <hi>Law-giver.</hi> And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doeth <hi>Plinius</hi> maintayne, &amp; avouch, <note place="margin">PLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIUS.</note> in his ſeaventh Booke of Naturall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie.</p>
                     <p>Now, as the Corne, and Meale ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, &amp; Bread baking, was firſt found by a Woman, Dame
<hi>Ceres,</hi> as ſaid is, ſo <note place="margin">CERES. ISIS.</note> is there another rare Dame, called <hi>Iſis,</hi> who found out the way, how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, and plow the land. And, ſhortlie after, other vertuous Women, in <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> haue invented the Siue; and ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14376:19"/> others, in <hi>Spaygne,</hi> the Bolting-cloath: as ſayeth <hi>Plinius,</hi> in his eyghteenth Booke.</p>
                     <p>More-over, in the beginning Men lived moſt Barbarouſlie, Groſslie, and Brutiſhlie, having not wherewith to cover their nakedneſſe, but the Shins of wilde Beaſts, and barks of Trees: vntill the time that the Women found out the making of Cloath. In which Arte Dame
<hi>Tannaquil,</hi> (or, as ſome <note place="margin">TANNA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUIL.</note> call her, <hi>Caja)</hi> was extraordinarie pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and expert: and, therefore, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Goddeſſe of good Houſe-wyues.</hi> But the firſt that ever began to ſpinne Wooll, was a comelie, fayre, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Virgine, in the Countrey of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> called <hi>Arachne:</hi> as teſtifieth
<hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHNE.</note> and <hi>Ovid,</hi> in his
<hi>Metamorph.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But I know not what would haue become of ſillie Man, had not Dame <hi>Pallas</hi> found our Flax and Hempe, and <note place="margin">PALLAS.</note> the invention of making of Linnen Cloath. For, I am ſure, that, without Linnen, Men would bee much fouler, and vncleaner than Beaſts: ſo that his Habitation would bee more odious, than the ſtall of <hi>Augia.</hi> And theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14376:20"/> enormities are all prevented, even by Women. Thus Men may vnderſtand, that all Heavenlie Gifts, and Graces, ſhew themſelues farre more excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in Women, than in Men.</p>
                     <p>And, I neede not to make much adoe, to proue, that the Women are, in no degree, ſo greedie, and avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as are vnhappie Men. And thus I durſt appeale to everie honeſt Mans Conſcience: yet, never-the-leſſe, I can hardlie paſſe by heere, to tell you how Queene
<hi>Semiramis</hi> approved this <note place="margin">SEMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAMIS. DARIUS.</note> on King
<hi>Darius:</hi> for ſhe cauſed build a coſtlie, and Sumptuous Tombe, vpon the which ſhe cauſed write this Poeſie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Who ſo deſireth gold, &amp; ſilver much, (ſuch. Breake down this Tombe, &amp; he ſhall find all</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And, as King <hi>Darius</hi> happened to come that way, and beholding the Tombe, and reading the ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hee cauſed open the ſame: and on the innerſide of the ſame ſtone was written thus;
<q>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Thou Graceleſſe Man, and full of Greedineſſe,</l>
                              <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14376:20"/>
                              <l>That Women doe ſurpaſſe thee, now confeſſe.</l>
                              <l>Hadſt thou beene other, but a catiue Wretch.</l>
                              <l>Thy Hands on dead Mens Tombes thou wouldſt not ſtretch.</l>
                           </lg> 
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſo finding nothing within, but duſt and clay, and ſeeing himſelfe ſo farre deceaved, this greedie Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Man departed, looking as angrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, as a March-Hare.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in his Church Hiſtories, <note place="margin">EUSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIUS.</note> wryteth greatlie to the juſt Prayſe of Women, by the example of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Origen:</hi> for, manie Martyrs on <note place="margin">ORIGEN</note> a day beeing condemned to bee burnt, by the Enemies of the Goſpell of CHRIST, this <hi>Origen</hi> was in the mynde, voluntarilie, and vnaccuſed, to haue ſuffered death with them, on the morrow. But his Mother, (happie Woman) beeing aware thereof, came quyetlie into his Chamber, the night before, &amp; tooke away all his Cloathes. So that when <hi>Origen</hi> roſe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with full reſolution, to ſacrifice himſelfe, with the other Martyrs, hee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14376:21"/> had nothing to put on: and ſo was faine to tarrie in his Chamber, a day or two, till GOD changed his mynde: and lived manie yeares after, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an excellent inſtrument in propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Goſpell of GOD; as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth till this day, by his worthie, and holie Wrytings.</p>
                     <p>Yet, before I conclude this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I muſt rehearſe vnto you two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Women, who in excellencie of learning, and Governament, were not behinde anie Men that ever wee reade of.</p>
                     <p>The firſt of theſe was a Woman borne in <hi>England,</hi> of Heroicke Parents, and her ſelfe of a loftie ſpirit, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ingenious wit: and having paſſed the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Schooles, at home, ſhee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>England,</hi> in Mans Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and came to <hi>Athens;</hi> which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at that tyme, flowriſhed, aboue all others, in Learning, and Policie: in which ſhe extraordinarilie ſtudied, and profited exceedinglie, calling her ſelfe <note place="margin">POPE IOHN.</note> 
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> And afterwardes, comming to
<hi>Rome,</hi> ſhee taught, and diſputed, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in the Schooles, in the habite of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14376:21"/> moſt graue Doctor: and was ſo well lyked of, that they thought her the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon of that Age. And after the death of <hi>Leo,</hi> the fourth of that name, Pope of
<hi>Rome,</hi> about the yeare of our LORD 852. ſhee was choſen Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> and governed that Place, with great wiſdome, in good Civilitie, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Peace, the ſpace of three yeares, two moneths, and foure dayes: and ended her lyfe with great Renowne.</p>
                     <p>Another rare, wiſe, and excellent Woman, was <hi>Theodoſia,</hi> Empreſſe of
<hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> who through the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Emperour, her Husband, who, ſeeing Diſturbances lykelie to fall out, in his Empire, cowardlie, left all, betooke himſelfe to a Cloſter, and became a Monke: and lykewyſe her Brother <hi>Zoc</hi> beeing ſlaine, ſhee gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Empyre her ſelfe; and that ſo valiantlie, and judiciouſlie, that ſhe was (out of meaſure) beloved of her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and feared of her Enemies, all the dayes of her lyfe: and departed this lyfe in peace, about the yeare of CHRIST 1050.</p>
                     <p>And, to conclude this Chapter, I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14376:22"/> ſpeake thus much, with pardon to the Women of theſe tymes, to follow the Vertue of theſe their aforeſayde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To Vertue, and to Honour, once in</hi> Rome,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Two ſtatelie Temples there erected was:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Where none might vnto Honours Temple come,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But firſt through Vertues Temple they muſt paſſe.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Which was an Embleme, and a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cument,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>That wee by Vertue muſt true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour win;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And that, that Honour ſhall be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> permanent,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Which onlie did from Vertue firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Then ſith theſe Women haue tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> Vertue wun,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>See yee with them the paths of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue run.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14376:22"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER IV. <hi>Of the Valiantneſſe, Boldneſſe, and Cowrage of Women; and of their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Battells; farre ſurpaſſing the engine, or Cowrage of Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch Striplings as take pleaſure, as farre as they may, to impeach the Honour and Credit of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and to denye their rare perfection in everie excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent thing, even aboue Man; let ſuch ſtand abacke, I ſay, and withdrawe themſelues, vnto theſe learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, who preferre the Valour, Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and bold-heartineſſe of Women, to all the Men that ever were: and, for this purpoſe, let them, with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, reade <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus, Trogus Pompeius, Juſtinus, Oroſius, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus, Plinius, Herodotus, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Solinus Pomponius, Mela,</hi> and manie others, in the renowned Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Amazones;</hi> where it is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhowne, that the juſt praiſe of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14376:23"/> in Martiall affaires alſo, farre aboue Men, hath ſounded through the World.</p>
                     <p>Now, theſe <hi>Amazones</hi> dwelt in <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia;</hi> this <hi>Scythia</hi> lying in North<hi>-Aſia;</hi> the which, now-adayes, is called <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria;</hi> whereby it is knowne from that <hi>Scythia</hi> which lyeth in <hi>Europe.</hi> And the <hi>Amozones</hi> having no King, but a Queene, called <hi>Orithie,</hi> together with <note place="margin">ORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE.</note> a valiant Ladie, whom the Queene made her Vice-Gerent, called <hi>Antiope.</hi> Theſe two Women governed the <hi>Amazones</hi> ſo wyſelie, and valiantlie, that they were feared of all their neyghbours: So that <hi>Euristeus</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian</hi> King, was compelled to intreat Great
<hi>Hercules</hi> himſelfe, to put on his Armour, and to helpe him againſt two Women, forſooth, who then ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie governed the <hi>Amazones,</hi> that his bowles quaked for feare of them.</p>
                     <p>Now, this <hi>Hercules,</hi> beeing pricked with Ambition, jealous of Honour, &amp; greedie for preferment, (as, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, Men haue ever beene) hee aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the forces that hee might: and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with him <hi>Theſeus,</hi> and other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14376:23"/> mightie Friends, and aſſiſtants, they imbarked themſelues to ſayle towards <hi>Scythia,</hi> agaynſt the Queene of the <hi>Amazones:</hi> and after great Skaithe of their owne people, are returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out victorie; not daring to bide bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when the Queene in proper perſon came to giue them Battell: but deſtroyed ſome of the Countrey with fire, and ſo fled away, lyke Men. But ſoone after that, the Queene, and her Forces, followed over, into
<hi>Europe,</hi> to bee avenged on the <hi>Gricks,</hi> and on <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risteus;</hi> where they made ſuch havock, on the Borders, and Frontures, of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that their King was faine to compone with the Queene, and to buy her out of his Countrey; Great <hi>Hercules</hi> being ſlayn: In token where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the <hi>Athenians</hi> hold him for their Patron till this day.</p>
                     <p>And a long time, thereafter, the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> going into <hi>Aſia,</hi> agaynſt the
<hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janes,</hi> and <hi>Pentheſilia,</hi> then beeing ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue <note place="margin">PENTHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SILIA.</note> Queene to <hi>Orithie,</hi> Queene of the <hi>Amazones,</hi> ſhee levied a gallant Armie, more Women, than Men, and came over, and aſſiſted the
<hi>Trojanes;</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14376:24"/> ſuch ſort, that through her ſtratagems, and feats of Armes, ſhee ſo defeated the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that they were almoſt vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie vndone; had it not beene for
<hi>Achilles,</hi> who ſubtillie deceaved that valiant Queene <hi>Pentheſilia,</hi> and ſhee
<note place="margin">PENTHE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>SILIA.</note> was ſlayne in Battell: wherethrough the reſt returned home; to their owne Countrey of <hi>Amazone,</hi> chooſing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queene, called
<hi>Thalistris.</hi> And this <hi>Thalistris</hi> governed, and reygned, <note place="margin">THALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRIS.</note> in great Wealth, and proſperitie, over the <hi>Amazones,</hi> even in the dayes of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, when as hee had Warres agaynſt the
<hi>Hircanites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And, whether for feare, or loue, I know not, yet <hi>Alexander</hi> never mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the
<hi>Amazones;</hi> but helde their Queene in great eſtimation, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
                     <p>But, after her deceaſe, when Men, forſooth, came to governe the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zones,</hi> all thinges went backwards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them: ſo that their Enemies prevayled: and, within ſhort tyme, that Kingdome was brought to nothing.</p>
                     <p>Againe, the Emperour, <hi>Claudius</hi> the ſecond, having Warres agaynſt the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14376:24"/> 
                        <hi>Gothes:</hi> and on a day, beeing victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious over them in Battell, himſelfe in proper perſon perceaved ſome valiant fighting Souldioures amongſt the
<hi>Gothes,</hi> exceeding manie others, in cowrage: which hee cauſed take aliue, as priſoners; but onlie ten in number. And when their Armour was laide off, theſe ten were perceaved to bee Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Whereat the Emperour ſtood greatlie amazed, and gaue them great praiſe, and rich Gifts, judging them to haue beene deſcended of the valiant <hi>Amazones.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And, lykewyſe, the Countrey of <hi>Francia Antartica,</hi> is extraordinarilie well governed, and defended, even by Women, till this day: as wryteth <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">THEVET ANGO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOZIN.</note> 
                        <hi>Angomozin,</hi> in his Diverſitie of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories.</p>
                     <p>Hearken yet vnto <hi>Lactantius,</hi> who famouſlie commendeth the women of
<hi>Lacedemonia;</hi> who iſſued foorth of their Citie, when their Enemies had moſt ſtronglie beſiedged them: and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themſelues ſo victoriouſlie, that few of their Enemies eſcaped. In teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication whereof, thoſe worthie <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimonian</hi>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14376:25"/> Women, even of the Golden Treaſure of their Enemies, they made a large Image of <hi>Venus,</hi> in compleat Armour, in token of their Victorie; to an everlaſting remembrance, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cowragement, to all ſucceeding Ages.</p>
                     <p>Neyther ought wee to paſſe by the Valiantneſſe, and Cowrage, of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of
<hi>Cimber;</hi> who, although their men were ſlayne, to the number of one hundreth fourtie thouſands, by <hi>Catulus,</hi> and <hi>Marius</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet the Women proved more valiant, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged the death of their Husbands; chooſing, rather, with them, to die, than to bee deflored of their Enemies. And this came to paſſe more than 90. yeares before the comming of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Yet to proceede, in the juſt prayſe of Women: <hi>Petrus Cirnitus,</hi> writing of
<note place="margin">PETRUS CIRNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUS. ZENO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIA.</note> Worthie Diſcipline, in his 26. Booke, and
14. Chapter, ſayeth, that <hi>Zenobia,</hi> Queene of <hi>Palmyren,</hi> fought a cruell Battell, agaynſt the Emperour <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and obtayned great victorie. Yet, becauſe he thought her but a Woman, hee made no great matter of it; but wrote vnto her, and bade her yeelde.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14376:25"/> But, ſhee, having receaved his letter, with a ſmiling Countenance, &amp; Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious mynde, anſwered him thus; It muſt not bee with Meſſiues, but with might of Armes, if thou ſhalt obtayne aniething at my hands: For, let thy groſſe vnderſtanding bee aſſured, that <hi>Cleopatra</hi> had rather want lyfe, than <note place="margin">CLEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PATRA. AENEAS SYL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIUS.</note> Honour.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes was Pope, and great Biſhop of the holie Citie of
<hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, declareth at length, that the land of
<hi>Bealme</hi> was long time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilie governed by Women.</p>
                     <p>But, becauſe all Hiſtories, both Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and Temporall, as well olde, as new, make ſo much mention, of the Valiantneſſe, &amp; Cowrage of Women, I neede not to tarrie anie longer heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon; but to goe forewardes, in the due prayſe of Women; declaring to the World, their other rare perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, alſo; even to the aſtoniſhment and baſhfulneſſe, of all their Gainſayers whatſoever: And ſo I conclude this Chapter, proceeding to another, with this great encowragement, to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14376:26"/> now of our tymes, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ever.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Let their Example bee a Spurre to you,</l>
                           <l>That yee their worthie Vertues may perſue.</l>
                           <l>Women they were, and you are even as much:</l>
                           <l>They were Victorious, you may even bee ſuch.</l>
                           <l>They had great Cowrage, guarded with good Skill:</l>
                           <l>Which Skill and Cowrage, Fortune, Grace, and Will,</l>
                           <l>I doe implore th' Almightie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow,</l>
                           <l>On each of you, the High, and eke the low.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14376:26"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER V. <hi>Of ſundrie good Women, who wittilie, and valiantlie, haue cleanſed whole Countreys, and Congregations, of cruell Tyrants, and Heretickes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd if men haue obtained anie prayſe and glorie on earth, by mayntayning their Kingdomes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, Townes, and other thinges of this world, by the loſſe of limbes and lyues; then, I am aſſured, that our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie women haue deſerved farre more happie fame, prayſe, and renowne, who haue not ſpared their vttermoſt endevours, painful travels, their goods, children, limbes, nor lyfe, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of things Aboue, as GODS true Religion, and the holie Goſpell of IESUS CHRIST.</p>
                     <p>It is ſayde in the Booke of <hi>Judeth,</hi> that when the pryde of <hi>Nabuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor</hi> was puffed vp even to the Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, giving commandement vnto <hi>Olofernes</hi>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14376:27"/> (chiefe captayne of his armie) to bring the whole world vnder his ſubjection. Where was ever heard tell of ſuch lyke pryde in Women? But what followed? Forſooth, the LORD ſent holie <hi>Judeth,</hi> into the campe of the <hi>Aſsyrians,</hi> (lying before <hi>Bethulia)</hi> and tooke off the head of the tyrant <hi>Olofernes,</hi> even with his owne ſword: whereby ſhee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited the hudge armie of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of GODS People, and preſerved her citie. But, becauſe I haue ſayde ſomewhat heereof, and of <hi>Deborah,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jael,</hi> before, in my ſecond Chapter; therefore I goe forwards, to others moe; whoſe number is ſo infinite, that this little volume can not contayne the hundreth part: onlie I ſhall recite a few, and ſo proceede to another ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, even in the juſt prayſe of Women bee it ſayde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abimelech,</hi> that Arch-tyrant, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his threeſcore and ten Brethren, deſtroyed the Citie of <hi>Sechem,</hi> burnt <note place="margin">IUDGES 8. 35. and 9. 1. 2. 3 4. &amp;c.</note> the Counſell-houſe, and ſowed the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with ſalt. And, not content with this, hee preſentlie beſiedged the Citie of <hi>Thebes:</hi> and having chaſed the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14376:27"/> people into a ſtrong Tower, hee came to the doore thereof, of purpoſe to ſet it on fyre, with his owne cruell handes. <note place="margin">IUDGES 9. 56. 7 53. 54. 2. SAM.
11. 21.</note> But a certaine woman, ſayth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, threw downe a piece of a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone vpon <hi>Abimelech</hi>'s head; ſo that his brayne pan was broken. Then cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed he a young man to thruſt his ſword thorow him: and ſo hee died ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie.</p>
                     <p>In this ſame manner died alſo King <hi>Pyrrhus:</hi> who lying in ſiedge before the Towne of <hi>Argoes,</hi> a woman threw a ſtone vpon his head. And being blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with blood, a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſed a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, called <hi>Zopyrus,</hi> to run him tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row with a Speare.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in his booke of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Women, ſpeaketh verie laudably of
<hi>Aretaphilia;</hi> who marvelouſlie, and <note place="margin">ARETA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHILIA</note> verie periculouſlie, delivered her owne Countrey, from the tyrannie of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> and
<hi>Leander:</hi> both which ſhe put to death, and cauſed <hi>Calniam</hi> to bee burnt, beeing the occaſion of their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie.</p>
                     <p>Stand yet abacke, yee Deſpyſers of WOMEN, and take example by <hi>Cyrus</hi>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14376:28"/> the Emperour: who (as long as his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſſe lived) being a good and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, afterwards became a cruell &amp; vnmercifull Tyrant. But what follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed? The Hiſtorie ſayeth, that <hi>Thomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> Queene of <hi>Scythia,</hi> waged Battell
<note place="margin">THOMY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIS.</note> agaynſt him: whom ſhe tooke, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed cut off his head. And, for a reward of his bloodie crueltie, ſhe put his head into a veſſell full of mens blood; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Satisfie nowe thy ſelfe with blood; which, here-to-fore, thou couldst never get anough.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>More-over: Amongſt the reſt of worthie Women, let vs ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of <hi>Ieane</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> or of <hi>Arke,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">IEANE of OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEANS.</note> (for whom the <hi>French-men</hi> haue great cauſe to praiſe GOD:) for by her god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Skill, and willing forewardneſſe, the kingdome of <hi>France</hi> was fred from conquering <hi>Engliſh-men:</hi> who had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſlie poſſeſſed that kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fourtie years together.</p>
                     <p>But yet, as the <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes valourous Conquerours: ſo alſo haue they ever beene knowne to bee verie mercifull Enemies, and friendlie Foes. For, though they had conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14376:28"/> all; yet, of their courteſie, they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the King of <hi>France</hi> to poſſeſſe <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> with ſome other adjacent little Townes, for his mayntaynance: whereby hee might ſpende everie day a Sheepe, (at the leaſt) and two Capons, beſides Leekes, Salats, &amp;c. as ſayeth <hi>Iohn Marconville,</hi> in his book of the
<hi>Prayſe of Women,</hi> chap. 7.</p>
                     <p>Now, I will not loſe my tyme, for the prſeut, to argue the matter, (with <hi>William Bellay</hi> of <hi>Lange,</hi> in his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Booke <hi>Deremilitari)</hi> concerning the aforeſayd <hi>Ieane,</hi> (named from <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colours,</hi> and called <hi>The Mayd of France,</hi> or <hi>The Mayd of Helpe)</hi> whether tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the hand of GOD, or by Witch-Craft, ſhe brought ſuch great things to paſſe. How-ſo-ever, true it was, that <hi>France,</hi> by her meanes, was ſet free at that tyme, all, except <hi>Cales,</hi> which the
<hi>Engliſh-men</hi> kept ſtill, from the dayes of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Valoys,</hi> till the Reygne of <hi>Heurie</hi> the ſecond<hi>:</hi> which was two hundreth, and eleven yeares.</p>
                     <p>But at laſt, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armie lying in ſiedge before the citie of
<hi>Campaigne,</hi> and <hi>Jeane</hi> making her ſelfe thither-wardes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14376:29"/> to relieue the <hi>French-men,</hi> ſhee was betrayed by <hi>John</hi> of
<hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and delivered vnto the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> who burnt her to powder at
<hi>Rowane,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>May,</hi> 1340.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>To testifie Shee had done good,</l>
                           <l>Her deeds were ſealed with her blood.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                     <p>And therefore,</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Let</hi> FORTVNE <hi>ſmyle, or frowne, bee ſtill content:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>In all</hi> Eſſayes <hi>beare ſtill an Heart true bent.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14376:29"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER VI. <hi>Of the wonderfull goodneſſe of GOD, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Man, whicth He hath wrought by Religious</hi> Women<hi>: And how by a Woman,</hi> Britayne <hi>first receaved the Christian Fayth.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vnto all men, who are not bereaft of their wits, and altogether voyd of Underſtanding, That the greateſt Benefite vnder the Sunne, is THE GIFT OF FAYTH, and TRVE BELIEFE; whereby wee come neare vnto GOD, frame our ſelues to loue and feare Him; and ſo attayne to the knowledge of His juſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and tender Mercies. And this great and excellent Gift of GOD, is manifeſted vnto Mankynde, (next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to His Sacred Word) even by choſen &amp; holie Women; whom it pleaſed GOD to make the firſt Heraulds of Chriſt's Glorious Reſurrection, as ſayde is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in our ſecond Chapter. And alſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14376:30"/> manie worthie Eccleſiaſticall Writers teſtifie, That <hi>Marie Magdalene, Martha,</hi> &amp;c. did firſt publiſh the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and preached CHRIST Crucified, and His Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, in the Countrey of <hi>Illyrica,</hi> which is nowe called <hi>Slavonia,</hi> and alſo in the Land of <hi>Provence:</hi> where they conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the people, and brought them to the true Fayth.</p>
                     <p>Wee reade of <hi>Apollos,</hi> a learned <hi>Jew</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> an eloquent Man, and mightie in the Scriptures: And altho hee was alreadie well inſtructed in the way of the LORD; yet <hi>Aquila,</hi> by the <note place="margin">ACTS 18. 24. 25. 26.</note> helpe of
<hi>Priſcilla,,</hi> his wyfe, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto him the way of GOD more perfectlie, than ever hee knew of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                     <p>And, the great King <hi>Agrippa</hi> was <note place="margin">ACTS 26. 27. 28. 29.</note> but almoſt perſwaded by <hi>Paul,</hi> to bee a Chriſtian.</p>
                     <p>But, to the contrarie, GOD had mercie on good <hi>Lydia,</hi> opened her <note place="margin">ACTS
16. 14. 15</note> heart: and not almoſt, but altogether made her His choſen Veſſell.</p>
                     <p>Reade the Chronicle of fayre <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and you ſhall vnderſtand, that in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14376:30"/> the dayes of King <hi>Egilbert,</hi> the whole Realme was infected with the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hereſie of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> And Saynct <hi>Auguſtine</hi> comming thither, to preach the Chriſtian Religion; by mediation of the Queene, after great, and ſerious paynes, and loving intreatie, the King gaue eare, and was converted, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his People. See, thus did
<hi>England,</hi> firſt receaue the true Fayth, by the meanes of a Woman; ſayeth
<hi>Gaguinus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hermigidus,</hi> King of <hi>Gothes,</hi> beeing <note place="margin">GAGUI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NUS.</note> infected with the Hereſie of <hi>Arrius,</hi> is alſo converted, and brought to the true acknowledgement of CHRIST cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, even by his Wyfe, <hi>Nigegond;</hi> as ſayeth the ſame
<hi>Gaguinus,</hi> in his ſecond Booke.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, thorow the earneſt travell, of <hi>Clotildis</hi> Queene of <hi>Perthan,</hi> the King
<hi>Clowis,</hi> her Husband, was baptized, and greatlie rejoyced, with thankſgiving vnto GOD, who had brought him from Darkneſſe, to Light, and that by the meanes of a Woman, ſayeth
<hi>John Marconville.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Amongſt aboundance of other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14376:31"/> Authors, it is manifeſt by <hi>Plutarch, Boccace,</hi> and <hi>Symphorian Champer,</hi> That manie men, both mightie and wyſe, haue gotten their beſt Education even by Women; and receaved from Them, next vnto GOD, their beſt and moſt wholſome Benefites: as well concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the good of the Soule, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the bodie. And this was more than manifeſt on <hi>Flavius Clemens,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Domician</hi> the Emperour. But now I will not tarrie vpon ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie Subject, leſt our pieviſh <hi>Diſgracers of Women,</hi> ſhould run mad, and altogether deſpare of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for their misbehaviour in chatting agaynſt Women. <note place="margin">MERCU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIUS TRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STUS.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus,</hi> duelie conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the wonderfull Goodneſſe of GOD towards Man, in Women, ſayth, That ſuch a Man, as in all manner of wayes, ſhowed not his full indevour in the Honour, yea, ſervice of Women, let him bee accurſed. And, that ſuch a Man, as avoydeth the Companie of Woman, let him bee buried quicke.</p>
                     <p>But, fooliſh, ſenſeleſſe, and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Man, who will not bee perſwaded
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14376:31"/> neyther by Reaſon, nor Trueth, to ſhun his objections, That they are but Men, and dead long agoe, whom I cite for my Warrandize, in the juſt prayſe of Women; let him hearken then, what GOD ſayeth vnto Righteous <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, In all that Sarah ſayeth vnto thee,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">GEN. 21. 12.</note> 
                        <hi>hearken vnto her voyce,</hi> ſayeth the Lord. Then, thou that wilt not hearken vnto the voyce of thy Gracious Wyfe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thee to bee a ſonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but rather of <hi>Satan,</hi> the Enemie of all Loue, Concord, and good Connſell.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thus doe we find, that Wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in all things, Health, happines, vnto the man ſtill brings: And yet envious vnbelieving Man, His hardned heart, hee never ſettle can, For to implore the Heavens, to be ſo kinde, To keepe her ſtate, according to her minde,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14376:32"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER VII. <hi>Of the Wiſedome, Learning, Diſcipline, and good Manners; wherein Women haue proven farre more excellent, and perfect, than Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, Care, &amp; Pains, which ſillie man hath beſtowed, to attayne vnto Wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Learning, and Good Manners; whereby their Names and Honours, might bee immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; is nowayes to bee compared with the wyſe, curious, zealous, vpright, pious, and religious induſtrie of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                     <p>For, indeed, Women haue excelled and exceeded, not onlie the Men of late tymes, and our recent Doctors; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the eldeſt, and wyſeſt Fathers, and Philoſophers; the which, to the juſt prayſe of Women, I dare take in hand to proue, as thus:</p>
                     <p>And, becauſe the <hi>Sybills</hi> are of the moſt Renowned Rememberance, from ancient Tymes, therefore, I thinke it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14376:32"/> not amiſſe, for the preſent, to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heere, the firſt place, and that verie ſhortlie, ſince <hi>Lactantius, Euſebius, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">LACTAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIUS. EUSEBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VS, &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>Oraſius,</hi> and others haue more worthilie ſet downe their prayſe, than it is poſſible for mee to imagine.</p>
                     <p>Now, the word <hi>Sybilla,</hi> is not the name of anie particular Woman; but doeth ſignifie,
<hi>Propheteſſe,</hi> or <hi>Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer,</hi> or, as <hi>Thomaſius</hi> ſayeth, a Woman
<note place="margin">THOMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIUS.</note> which hath the ſpirit of propheſie.</p>
                     <p>And of theſe <hi>Sybillaes</hi> were ten in number; the firſt was called <hi>Perſica,</hi>
2. <note place="margin">TEN SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BILLS.</note> 
                        <hi>Lybia,</hi> 3. <hi>Delphica,</hi> 4.
<hi>Cumaea,</hi> 5. <hi>Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thraea,</hi> 6. <hi>Samia,</hi> 7. <hi>Cumana,</hi> 8.
<hi>Helleſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> 9. <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and the 10. <hi>Tyburtina.</hi> And all theſe, even long before the comming of our bleſſed MESSIAS did propheſie no leſſe, than was ſet downe by the holie Prophets, in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, concerning the Hebrew Childe, even CHRIST, our Redeemer.</p>
                     <p>But, amongſt theſe <hi>Sybills,</hi> there were two farre more renowned than the other, to wit, <hi>Cumana,</hi> and <hi>Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threa.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">CUMENA ERY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THREA.</note> Theſe two were in the dayes of our Ancient Fathers, and excelled all the Men of thoſe dayes, in perfection,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14376:33"/> Knowledge, Learning, and Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as can teſtifie their goodly books, decored with golden Sentences, extant till this day; telling, of the ende of the World, of the day of Iudgement, of Empyres, and Kingdomes, of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, Congregations, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke Governament, and manie other worthie things, even in the Booke of <hi>Revolution;</hi> wherevnto the wyſe and ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Romans,</hi> had ever their recourſe, and tooke counſell thereat, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Cicero,</hi> in his ſecond Booke of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination; <note place="margin">CICERO</note> ſaying, that the Sentences of the <hi>Sybills,</hi> in thoſe dayes, had as much authoritie, as now-a-dayes the holie Scripture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> ſpeaketh of an olde <note place="margin">AULUS GELLIUS</note> Woman, which came to the prowde King <hi>Tarquin,</hi> and brought with her <note place="margin">TAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUIN.</note> nyne Bookes, asking him, if hee would buy them? <hi>Tarquin</hi> asking the pryce of the Bookes; ſhee ſaid 300 Ducates. And whiles hee Skoffed at her, ſhee tooke three of the Bookes, and burnt them in the fire. Then ſhee asked, if he would giue 300 Ducates for the other ſixe? But ſeeing hee regarded her not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14376:33"/> yet, ſhe burnt other three. Then hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to repent, and ſayd, Woman, thou haſt burnt ſixe Bookes; what wilt thou haue for the other three? No leſſe, ſaid ſhee, than the pryce of the whole nyne; taking the hinmoſt three vp, to throw them into the fire. But hee ſtayed her, and gaue her the money for them. And when hee peruſed, and conſidered the Bookes, hee was almoſt beſides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for want of the other ſixe. Yet, thorow thoſe three Bookes, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a better man than of before.</p>
                     <p>Beſides theſe <hi>Sybills,</hi> wee ought to keepe in rememberance the worthie Queene of
<hi>Sheba,</hi> which ſome call <hi>Nicaula,</hi> and others <hi>Mangueda;</hi> who
<note place="margin">MAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUEDA.</note> bare ſuch a loue to Wiſdome, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that ſhee came from the vttermoſt parts of the world, to heare the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Salomon;</hi> as you may reade in <note place="margin">SALO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON. 1. KINGS 10.</note> the firſt booke of Kings: and is greatly commended in the Goſpell, even by CHRIST Himſelfe; who ſharplie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved thoſe wicked Men, Scribes and Phariſees: and, (even in the juſt prayſe of Women bee it ſayde) Hee ſayeth, That that one Woman, ſhould <note place="margin">MATTH.</note>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14376:34"/> ryſe vp in judgement, and condemne that whole male generation.</p>
                     <p>Now, this Queene of <hi>Sheba,</hi> (or of the South) put the wyſe <hi>Salomon</hi> to his vttermoſt ſhifts in diſputation: for ſhee reaſoned with him, from the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope branch, vnto the Cedar trees: that is, concerning the vertue and qualitie of the ſmalleſt Herbs, to the talleſt trees in <hi>Lebanus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And yet I proceede in this ſubject, to the juſt prayſe of Women, thus.</p>
                     <p>The learned writings of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">PYTHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GORAS. DAMA.</note> had never come to light, if his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Dama,</hi> had not beene of learned Skill, to interpret the ſame, after the deceaſe of her father. <note place="margin">ARETA. ARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PUS. METRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTUS.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Queene <hi>Areta</hi> was ſo wonderfullie well learned, that her ſonne
<hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> had no other to teach him, but her ſelfe: and therefore was hee called
<hi>Metrodidactus;</hi> that is to ſay, Taught of his Mother.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> the daughter of the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Oratour <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> made ſuch a learned Oration publicklie in the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> and with ſuch a comelie ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and excellent modeſt behaviour,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14376:34"/> that ſhee is regiſtrated in the imperiall Annalls of ſtatelic
<hi>Rome;</hi> even to the example of all enſuing Ages, Thus may wee know, That</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Good Women, then, were never yet combynde;</l>
                           <l>But evermore haue borne as braue a mynde,</l>
                           <l>As did the men in Ages what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</l>
                           <l>Their Cowrage, Skill, and Will, was conquer'd never.</l>
                           <l>Therefore I'll forwardes, in our Mothers prayſe,</l>
                           <l>Of whom, next vnto GOD, wee holde our lyfe and dayes.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14376:35"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER VIII. <hi>Of Women, who not onlie ſurpaſſed Men in Poëſie: but alſo overthrew the learned Doctors, and Philoſophers, in Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">CORIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NA.</note> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt other worthie learned Poëticall Women,
<hi>Corinna</hi> is ſaid to haue ſurpaſſed the Poët <hi>Pindar,</hi> verie farre, in compiling of lyricke verſe.<note place="margin">PINDAR</note> 
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">THEANO</note> Alſo Heroicke <hi>Theano</hi> bare away the prayſe from all the poëticall Men in her dayes; which were not a few, neyther vnexpert.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">SOCRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES.</note> The Renowned <hi>Socrates</hi> thought it no ſhame to confeſſe, that hee had gotten great Knowledge in Poëſie, by the inſtruction of the famous Ladie <hi>Aſpaſia.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ASPASIA LEAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA. THEO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STUS.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And Ladie <hi>Leantia</hi> overcame that great Philoſopher <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
                     <p>Now, becauſe <hi>Plato</hi> ſaw, that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Learning, and Knowledge,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14376:35"/> grew to ſuch an height in Women, hee envyed their aſpyring eſtate; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a Law, and Ordinance; That no Woman-kynde ſhould frequent the Schooles, or bee brought vp in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But, ſillie man, that hee was<hi>!</hi> the meanes that hee made to hinder women of learning, proved but a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to ſtirre them forwards therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. For then, more eagerlie than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, manie worthie Virgins, (ſuch as <hi>Laſcenia, Ariota,</hi> and others) neglected
<note place="margin">LASCE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA. ARIOTA</note> not carneſtlie to haunt the Schoole of <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe, in mans cloathing; and profited greatlie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cornelia,</hi> the wyfe of <hi>Scipio,</hi> was ſo <note place="margin">CORNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIA.</note> excellent well learned, that ſhee hath left behinde her, even to the due praiſe of Women, manie excellent and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned verſes, called <hi>Cornificia;</hi> which <note place="margin">CORNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICIA.</note> beeing juſtlie interpreted, ſignifieth as much, as ſhee was a ſhyning, and glancing Light, or Lampe, yeelding Light, in Learning, to the darkened men of her age.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caria</hi> and <hi>Afrania,</hi> beeing but poore <note place="margin">CARIA. AFRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA.</note> Women, yet grew ſo expert in the Lawes, that the Magiſtrates compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14376:36"/> them to lay away their Diſtafs, and ſpindles: and they ſo diſcuſſed the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt matters, which came before the Counſell, that they were holden in great Reverence, and honoured of all: and gayned more loue, and benefite, than all the Men-lawyers in that land.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Diodore</hi> of <hi>Sicilia</hi> had fiue Children, <note place="margin">DIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DORE.</note> and all were daughters: and each of them ſo exceeded other, in Learning, Behaviour, and good Manners, that certaine good Lawes of their making, are yet in full effect in that Countrey.</p>
                     <p>But, to ſhun the objections of the Calumniatours of Women, who may ſeeme to ſay, that I produce too manie examples of Heathen Women: and the Heathen ſet their onlie Felicitie, and
<hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> in the attayning to the perfection and knowledge of thinges of this lyfe: therefore, I turne againe, to the worthie teſtimonies of our Eccleſiaſticall Wryters, and good examples of Chriſtian Women.</p>
                     <p>The worthie <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth, in <note place="margin">EUSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIUS. IEMNA.</note> his Church Hiſtories, that <hi>Memna,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Emperour <hi>Alexander Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> had ſuch an earneſt zeale to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14376:36"/> Learning, and Vertue, that ſhe ſent to <hi>Antioch,</hi> deſiring holie
<hi>Origen</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ORIGEN</note> to come vnto her, even to inſtruct her yet farder in the way of Salvation: of whoſe comming ſhee rejoyced great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, heard his doctrine, and proved a worthie Matron in true Religion, and mightilie inſtructed others.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tecla,</hi> a Mayde-Diſciple to Saynct <note place="margin">TECLA.</note> 
                        <hi>Paul,</hi> excelled manie of his Man-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, in Wiſdome, Learning, and Godlineſſe, ſayeth the ſame <hi>Euſebius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Saynct <hi>Katharine,</hi> a Virgin of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">SAINCT KATHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RINE.</note> overthrew fiftie learned Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, in weyghtie matters of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amia,</hi> and the foure daughters of <note place="margin">AMIA.</note> Saynct
<hi>Philip,</hi> were propheteſſes of the new Teſtament, in the Churches of
<hi>Philadelph.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the dayes of Saynct <hi>Jerome,</hi> were aboundance of learned, wyſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<note place="margin">GERON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA. FABIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LA. &amp;C.</note> Women, ſuch as <hi>Gerontia, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biola, Furia, Marcella, Demetridis, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> and manie others: vnto whom Saynct <hi>Jerome</hi> wrote manie learned Epiſtles; and they to him againe.</p>
                     <p>Heere may <hi>Dumea Angia,</hi> a Virgin, <note place="margin">DUMEA ANGIA.</note>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14376:37"/> Ladie of Honour to the Queene of <hi>Portugall,</hi> of 22 yeares old, take place; who wrote vnto Pope <hi>Paulus,</hi> (the third of that name, Biſhop of <hi>Rome)</hi> in fiue languages; to wit, in <hi>Latine, Greeke, Hebrew, Chaldaicke,</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicke.</hi> So that that Pope ſeeing her to be ſuch an excellent Scholler, indeede, was faine to vſe the helpe of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: otherwyſe, it had beene vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to haue ſent her any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Anſweres. This happened about the yeare of GOD 1548.</p>
                     <p>And in thoſe dayes dwelt a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> woman in <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Iſobell Roſier;</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ISOBEL ROSIER. SCOTUS SUBTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUS.</note> who in publicke audience conſtructed, and interpreted the bookes of <hi>Scotus Subtilus:</hi> who in thoſe dayes was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the ſubtileſt Fellowe in the world.</p>
                     <p>Alſo we reade of manie Noble Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yea, and of Queens, who haue ſo highlie excelled in Learning, and ſo ſkillfull in ſundry Languages, that they themſelues anſwered the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours ſent from anie Nation whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Which their block-headed Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes could not doe: and therefore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14376:37"/> muſt holde themſelues as mute, as doe the Myce in preſence of the Cat.</p>
                     <p>And thus, in the juſt prayſe of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I conclude this Subject, haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towardes another: for Their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perfections are ſo manie, great and wonderfull, that I muſt needes confeſſe,</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The more I gaze agaynst the Sunnes cleare light,</l>
                           <l>The more am I distracted of my ſight.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAPTER IX. <hi>Of the Chastitie, Modeſtie, and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie in</hi> WOMEN, <hi>both Wyues and Mayds: to the example of luxurious, vitious, and libidinous Men.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S amongſt the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men, there be ſome more groſſ and ſhamefull, than others: Even ſo amongſt the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying perfectious Graces in WOMEN,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14376:38"/> there are ſome more laudable, and of greater eſtimation.</p>
                     <p>And as <hi>Leacherie</hi> is a capitall Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Man, and ruleth in him as a Prince of all other Vices: Even ſo CHASTITIE in WOMAN, is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt poynt of Her Perfection, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in Her, as the Princeſſe of all other Vertues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Xenocrates</hi> ſayeth, that although a <note place="margin">XENO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRATES HELENA</note> Woman had the fayrneſſe of Queene <hi>Helen,</hi> the wiſdome of the queene of the <hi>South,</hi> and the riches of <hi>Craeſus;</hi> yet if ſhee want Chaſtitie, and puritie of bodie, ſhee is of no value, but lyke the blaſted ſlowre, and withered graſſe, which is troden vnder feete.</p>
                     <p>Yea, Chaſtitie is a Womans owne element, without the which ſhee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſubſtantiall, no more than the fowles without ayre, and the fiſhes without water. For as long as a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath Chaſtitie, (ſayeth an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Father) ſhe hath all good things, and is all thinges: but wanting That, ſhee hath no good thing, nor is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                     <p>And, this is almoſt the ſaying of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14376:38"/> chaſte <hi>Lucretia,</hi> that in Woman all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues <note place="margin">LUCRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA.</note> were fled away, when ſhee was once defiled.</p>
                     <p>And, it is true, that <hi>Lucretia</hi> ſpake not this in an vnadvyſed manner, or lightlie, in a ſpleane, or that ſhee ſayde the thing ſhee thought not: no, no; for ſhee ſealed her words, even with her owne Blood, GOD wots, after that <note place="margin">TAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUIN.</note> prowde <hi>Tarquine</hi> had violentlie defiled her.</p>
                     <p>But, our Chriſtian Women haue no fayrer example of cleanlie Chaſtitie, than in
<hi>Suſanna;</hi> who chooſed rather <note place="margin">SUSANNA</note> to loſe her lyfe, than to commit ſuch vncleane wickedneſſe. <note place="margin">THE chaſte Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of SALIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BURIE.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo, it is ſteadfaſtlie affirmed in the Chronicles of <hi>England,</hi> that one of their Kings, at the ſight of the fayre Counteſſe of <hi>Saliſburie,</hi> deſired her, to his luſtfull appetite, her Husband being in <hi>France.</hi> But, that good Woman, beeing readier to ende her lyfe, with a Dagger, than to ſatisfie his filthie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the King ſtayed her hand. Then ſhee beſought the King, that ſhe might firſt ſlay her Husband; and then ſhee would bee readie to pleaſure him in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14376:39"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14376:39"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:14376:40"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14376:40"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14376:41"/> anie thing. Thy Husband, ſayde the King, is in <hi>France.</hi> Nay, quod ſhee, hee is lodged here in myne Heart; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let mee kill him, that hee bewray vs not. Which wordes, and chaſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the Counteſſe, put the King in aſtoniſhment; ſo that hee feared GOD, left off his Deviliſh purpoſe, and helde that Ladie in Honour all his dayes.</p>
                     <p>The Tyrant <hi>Maxentinus,</hi> (ſayeth <note place="margin">EUSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIUS.</note>
                        <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in his eyght Booke, Chap. 17) ſent his ſervants for a comelie Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, in
<hi>Rome,</hi> named <hi>Sophrania,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flore <note place="margin">SOPHRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA.</note> her of her Virginitie. And when the Servantes had tolde her their meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, ſhee deſired them to ſtay, till ſhee attyred her ſelfe in her beſt array, that their Lord might the better accept of her. And going to her Chamber, ſhee fell downe on her Face, and cryed to the GOD of Heaven, to delyver her from anie ſuch filthie action. And whiles the wicked Sergeants would not ſtay, but beat vpon her Chamber doore, to take her ſpeedilie foorth, by violence; ſhe lifted vp her Eyes, Heart, and Mynde, towards Heaven; and with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14376:41"/> pen-knyfe, bereaft her ſelfe of lyfe: chooſing, farre rather, to offer her cleanlie Soule to GOD, and vndefiled Corpſe to the Graue, by Death, than to liue, and abide the wicked Pollution of filthie leacherous Man.</p>
                     <p>Yea, the ſame holie <hi>Euſebius,</hi> writeth <note place="margin">EUSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BIUS.</note> of an infinite number of other Wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who wyſelie, and valiantlie, haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the cleanneſſe of Bodie: &amp; haue not onlie ventred, (but alſo loſt) their lyues therefore.</p>
                     <p>And not onlie is this probable of Chriſtian Women: but alſo amongſt the verie Heathen, and Pagans, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrated aboundance of Women, who did, farre rather, loſe all the World, yea, lyfe, and all, before they would loſe their Honour.</p>
                     <p>Sainct <hi>Hieronymus,</hi> wryting againſt <note place="margin">HIERO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NYMUS.</note>
                        <hi>Joyinian,</hi> telleth of very many Women, who were of ſuch cleanlie Condition, Diſpoſition, and Qualitie, that neither Goods, Lyfe, nor Death, was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde with them, to their vndefiled Honeſtie. <note place="margin">A THEBAN MAYD.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And a Mayde of <hi>Theban,</hi> beeing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed, by a <hi>Macedonian,</hi> corbed her
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14376:42"/> heavie paſſions, for a day or two, till ſhee got occaſion to ſlay him: which ſhee valourouſlie performed with her owne hands. Then, rejoycing greatly, that GOD had given her ſtrength to bee avenged on ſuch a Villane, ſhee with-drew her ſelfe to the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where ſhe lived ſolitarilie all her dayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chiomara,</hi> the wyfe of <hi>Ortiagent,</hi> was <note place="margin">CHIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MARA.</note> taken in battell, by a Captayn who vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlie abuſed her. But ſhortly after her ranſom was ſent, and ſhe was to depart homewards. Now ſhee requeſted this Captayne, to convoy her a little piece of her journey: which he did verie wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie. And, ſhe having conſpired his death with her ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſhe drew him a little from the way, (whereof this Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher grew verie amorous, thinking to take his luſtfull leaue of that fayre La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) where foure of her ſervantes lay privilie, who helde him faſt, while ſhee took off his head, which ſhe carried to her husband, and threw it at his feete. Whereat he being amazed, ſayd, <hi>Thou wicked woman, wherefore hast thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this treaſon? Trueth and fidelitie</hi>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14376:42"/> 
                        <hi>ought to bee kept with our verie enemies. Yes,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>you ſay true: but it is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trueth nor Honestie for me, to let anie man liue that hath lyen with mee, except myne owne Huſband.</hi> Then her Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the matter rightlie, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her the more entirelie; and he, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the whole Countrey, hold her in great honour, all her dayes.</p>
                     <p>A <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Wyfe being ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſued by a leacherous Lubber, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, that ſhee could not giue that which was never her owne: <hi>For,</hi> quod ſhee, <hi>whyle I was a Damoſell, my Virginitie pertayned to my Parentes, and now it is myne owne Huſbandes.</hi> So this leacherous Logger-head left off his ſute, and tooke his <hi>Leaue</hi> without <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> looking as though his noſe had beene bleeding.</p>
                     <p>Reade, I pray you, <hi>Munſterus,</hi> in <note place="margin">MUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERUS. GRANT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZIO.</note> his Deſcription of the World, and alſo worthie <hi>Grantzio,</hi> in the Chronicles of
<hi>Germanie:</hi> where men ſhall finde ſuch plentie of the prayſe of Women con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chaſtitie; and ſuch loathſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in men concerning their deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble filthie viciouſneſſe; that if there be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14376:43"/> anie ſpunke eyther of Grace or Shame left in them, let them bow to women, and cry <hi>Pecaavi;</hi> and let all ſuch as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happilie are fallen into that damnable fact of Blaſphemie, or rayling, or ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing agaynſt Women, eyther in word or writ; let all ſuch, I ſay, bluſh, and bee aſhamed: and, without ſpeedie and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick repentance, not onelie confuted, but confounded for ever. And thus, in the juſt prayſe of Women, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to another Subject. For, though I ſhould aske vngratefull man,</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Wherein haue Women not ſurpaſſed Men,</l>
                           <l>In Good? They'll anſwere mee I know not when.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14376:43"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER X. <hi>Of the great and wonderfull Wiſdome in</hi> WOMEN: <hi>to the high Glorie of GOD, and great Benefit of Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd if our wicked, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and witleſſe Vilependers of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Sexe, could yet at laſt begin to conſider, and looke to the Right hand; caſting off that blind-board wherewith
<hi>Satan,</hi> the fat her of <hi>Envy,</hi> hath ſo long over-ſyled &amp; blind-folded the eies of their Underſtanding; then might they happilie, even to their owne credit and advantage, clearlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and confeſſe the ſingular Grace of GOD, in every degree, and in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure, proceeding more from WOMEN, than from Men. And ſo beeing come to themſelues, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging their haynous tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion agaynſt this Angelicall Sexe of Women, they would not fayle to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Poët <hi>Steſichoris,</hi> who vnadvy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedlie
<note place="margin">STESI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHORIS.</note> in his verſes had rayled agaynſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14376:44"/> fayre <hi>Helene</hi> of <hi>Greece:</hi> but when hee <note place="margin">IELEN.</note> rightlie vnderſtood himſelfe, he recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all what hee had eyther ſayde or written before: and wrote excellentlie in her prayſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation. Then why may not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch qualitie (with <hi>Steſichoris)</hi> turne both Notes &amp; Coates, ſince now-a-dayes ſo manie even of other qualities alſo willinglie adjoyne their Forces with them?</p>
                     <p>Nowe, amongſt all other gracious Ornaments, and ornamentall Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Graces, wherewith Women are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, is WISDOME, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with even from the Cradle they are ſtill decored and cloathed, as is moſte manifeſt as well by the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as all other true Hiſtories, both Eccleſiaſticall and Civill.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>the rayling of men agaynſt women,</hi> ſhoweth them to be the ſonnes of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed curſing <hi>Shimei,</hi> who rayled on bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bleſſing <hi>David.</hi> And as
<hi>David</hi>'s Bleſſing returned to himſelfe, even ſo did <hi>Shimei</hi>'s Curſing returne vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alſo. And ſo bee it vnto all thoſe curſed men, who implore not the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14376:44"/> that <hi>All Bleſsing</hi> bee vpon WO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN, that MAN may get part.</p>
                     <p>Looke to the wiſdome of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">GENES 27.</note> who procured her Husband <hi>Iſaac</hi> his bleſſing vnto <hi>Iaakob</hi> her youngeſt ſon, whereas
<hi>Iſaac</hi> himſelfe was purpoſed (that ſame verie day) to haue beſtowed it on
<hi>Eſau</hi> his eldeſt ſonne. For, ſillie man, as he was blind of bodie, ſo alſo in mynde, and knewe not that it was the LORD'S doing, as <hi>Rebecca</hi> knew, that <hi>the elder muſt ſerue the younger.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nowe, the men may ſtay their boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting agaynſt Women, (even by this example of
<hi>Iaakob</hi> and <hi>Eſau)</hi> in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">MATTH 26</note> of
<hi>Antiquitie;</hi> well remembering that <hi>the elder muſt ſerue the younger.</hi> For they ſolde their birth-right, for thirtie pieces of Silver, and ſo became portio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with
<hi>Barabbas,</hi> that laudable ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Murderer.</p>
                     <p>Agayne, if <hi>Antiquitie</hi> of men may beare anie ſway agaynſt women, I am aſſured the Devill is more ancient than men, being before them. And, as much as man can thinke himſelfe better than woman, becauſe he was firſt, I thinke the Devill may as well think ſuch like,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14376:45"/> becauſe <hi>Hee</hi> was before man. I will ſay nothing heere of the
<hi>Antiquitie</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Religion,</hi> till theſe miſtie muggie vnwholſome vapours of <hi>Idolatrie</hi> which infect my brayne, bee ſomewhat diſabled by the reflex of <hi>Titan</hi> from his higheſt Spheare.</p>
                     <p>But let vs goe on to our Purpoſe, in ſhowing this great Gift of Wiſdome in Women.</p>
                     <p>Wyſe <hi>Abigaill</hi> is highlie to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and her churliſh husband
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> greatlie to bee condemned, for his vncharitable dealing with <hi>David</hi> in his great neceſſitie. Wherby he had almoſt brought Deſtruction to himſelfe, and all his Familie, yea, and a horrible ſinne <note place="margin">1. SAM. 25.</note> vpon <hi>David,</hi> had not wyſe <hi>Abigaill</hi> prevented the ſame in tyme.</p>
                     <p>There was <hi>a wyſe woman</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiedged Citie of <hi>Abell</hi> of
<hi>Bethmaachah,</hi> ſayeth the Scripture, who delivered <note place="margin">2. SAM. 20.</note> the diſtreſſed Citie, even by the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of one wicked man, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt bene the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole Citie, named <hi>Sheba,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> called the <hi>Youngeſt,</hi> was ſo fooliſh, that hee would
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14376:45"/> put his Seale and ſubſcription vnadvy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedlie to anie Wrytinges that were brought vnto him, without eyther rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or hearing the ſame. Which his Siſter
<hi>Plucheria</hi> wyſelie conſidering what great evill might enſue thereby, ſhe bethought her, how ſhe might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilie prevent all occaſion of offence which might happen thorow her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſimplicitie, and to ingraff in him more deepe and ſolid vnderſtanding.</p>
                     <p>So this <hi>Plucheria</hi> cauſed a fayre wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">PLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHERIA</note> to frame a goodlie Commiſſion to looke vnto, the contents whereof was, <hi>That</hi> EVBOCE, (which was his owne Empereſſe, &amp; whom he beloved moſt dealy) <hi>ſhould be diſherited of all her Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſtripped of all fayre Cloathing; and being wrapped in ſacking, ſhould lye in a darke Dungeon ſeaven years. And if ſhee lived that long, then was ſhee ordayned, to worke naked amongſt the chayned ſlaues, all the reſt of her dayes.</hi> This Decree the Emperour too raſhly ſubſcribed, which was preſentlie delivered vnto his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who came ſpeedilie therewith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him, deſiring him that her name might alſo be incert in that Decree, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14376:46"/> for ſhee vowed to take a part of all thinges with the Empreſſe, as well evill as good, woe as weale, yea, and to liue and die with her.</p>
                     <p>The Emperour beeing amazed to heare his ſiſter ſpeake thus, ſayd, <hi>My loving Siſter, what meane you? I meane,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>to liue and die with thy Wyfe, whom thou haſt cruelly condemned, without knowing or asking the cauſe why.</hi> And, as one in a great furie, throwing the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at him, ſayd moreover, <hi>Haue there thyne own hand and Seale: it can not now be mended: but wryte downe my name alſo, and we will goe to priſon together: for nothing but Death ſhall be able to part vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And when hee ſaw, and vnderſtood the matter conſideratiuelie, hee cryed with a lowde voyce, deſiring GOD &amp; Man to forgiue him, ſent for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and on his knees, (ſhee falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his neck halfe dead) hee beſought her to forgiue him: which ſhe willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie granted. And giving them both great thanks, he never did ſo agayne.</p>
                     <p>The Duke of <hi>Caſtilia</hi> being impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned <note place="margin">THE Dutches of CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STILIA.</note> for treaſon agaynſt his brother the king, his wyfe got leaue to viſit
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14376:46"/> him in Priſon: where ſhee chaunged Cloathes with him, putting his vpon her, and hers vpon him, and ſent him out of the Priſon, and tarried therein her ſelfe; willing to ſuffer anie Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yea, to die for him, if it had ſo fallen out. But when the jaylour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved the matter, hee told the king, how that becauſe his Majeſtie had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven acceſſe to the Dutches of <hi>Caſtilia</hi> to come to her husband in Priſon, ſhee had beguiled them, and ſent him away in her cloathes, and remayned in the Priſon with his cloathes vpon her ſelf, and was verie willing to ſuffer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever could bee layd to her husband's charge. Which when the king vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, hee ſent privatelie for her, and cauſed his Queen giue her of her own rich Attire: and ſending his great Seale for her husband, forgaue him freelie, vpon good conditions: and ſent them home with great Honour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Plutarch</hi> maketh mention of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">PLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARCH.</note> in
<hi>Lydia,</hi> who would haue nothing done but making of Golde, with all his people; neglecting all manner of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, Huſwyuerie, and all other Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14376:47"/> So that the whole land was overgone with Rubbiſh, Briers, and Thorns. Which his wyſe Wyfe well remarking and conſidering, on a day her husband, with the whole people, being away to the making of Gold, and ſhee at home, with her maydes making readie their Dinner, ſhee prepared the ſimilitude of all manner of meat, roaſt and ſodden, everie thing in its owne forme and colour, and all of pure gold, and nothing elſe. Now her husband comming home hungrie from the Mynes, with his great companie, ſate downe to Meat, with well-prepared ſtomacks. And drawing out their ſharp Thittles, hee to a diſh, and he to a diſh: but could not cut, for all was Golde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereat they took great delight for a ſhort ſpace: but their bellies perſwaded their eyes to ſomewhat elſe. Then <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">THE wyfe of PY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIUS.</note> deſired his wyfe to take that mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> away, and giue them others. So ſhee brought other kyndes of Bread and Meat, alſo of pure Golde, ſtill ſo long that hee was almoſt mad for hunger and began to chafe moſte horriblie Wherevpon ſhe replyed, that ſhe could
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14376:47"/> giue him no other than his Countrey afforded, and ſuch as hee brought vnto her: For, ſayde ſhee, you haue forſaken Husbandrie, our land lieth waſte, corns haue we none, our beaſts run wild vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mountayns, &amp; traffique with other Nations haue wee none: wherewithall then would ye haue me to ſatisfie your hunger, or cloathe your nakedneſſe? Golde onlie is the fruit of your handes: eat it, and bee filled; put it on, and bee cloathed therewith; for I haue nought elſe to giue you. And whyle they gazed one vpon another, ſhe ran, and brought ſome other meat, both groſſe, and not much of it, wherewith they were fayne to be contented for that tyme.</p>
                     <p>But afterwards <hi>Pythius</hi> took ever his wyues counſell about him, employed his people in Husbandrie, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Vertue, made Golde alſo, were Traffiquers with other Nations, and ſo became a moſt flowriſhing Countrey. And all by the wiſdome and fore-ſight of his worthie WYFE.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thus Golde, and All, good Women can ſubdue,</l>
                           <l>And proue at all tymes to their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands true.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14376:48"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER XI. <hi>Of the conſtant ſteadfaſtneſſe in Women, not onlie ſuffering cruell Tormentes, but alſo horrid Death, for the Teſtimonie of</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, our GOD, who is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good work doeth often tymes make choyſe of weake Inſtruments, and ſuch as vnwyſe men count fooles; ever to manifeſt His great Power, and make His Glorie knowne to all the worlde; By abaſing the worldlie wyſe, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their wiſdome into follie; By put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the mightie from their ſeate, and exalting the humble and meeke; By ſending the rich empti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> away, &amp; filling the hungrie with good things, &amp;c. Which is more than mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by an innumerable number of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<hi>:</hi> who altho by nature they bee but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14376:48"/> weak veſſels; yet thorow influence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aboue, manie of them haue proven more ſtrong and ſteadfaſt in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt and greateſt Matters, than anie men that ever were: and eſpeciallie in mayntayning &amp; defending of the true and Chriſtian Fayth: yea, and ſuffered for the ſame, not onlie tyrannicall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but alſo cruell Death it ſelfe, notwithſtanding of the womanlie ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of their moſt comlie propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable featurall perſonages.</p>
                     <p>A Chriſtian Mayd in <hi>France,</hi> named <hi>Blandine,</hi> in the great Perſecution of
<note place="margin">BLAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DINE.</note> CHRIST'S Members there, vnder the Emperour <hi>Severus,</hi> about the yeare of our LORD 178, was taken, and bound to a Stake, with ſtrong threatninges to burne her, or elſe to renounce the Chriſtian Fayth. But ſhe continued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycinglie ſteadfaſt. Then brought they wilde beaſtes, to feede vpon her fleſh, and began to let them byte her tender corpſe. Yet nevertheleſſe ſhee ſhrunke not a jot: but the faſter that the Serpents did byte her, the lowder ſhe cryed, <hi>I am a Chriſtian, I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:</hi> looking vp, and calling earneſtlie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14376:49"/> to the GOD of Heaven, to giue her ſtrength and patience, that ſhee might bee worthie to finiſh her lyfe to the Glorie of His Name. Now, her tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments laſted ſo long, and ſhee endured ſo ſteadfaſt, that the verie Executioner ſtood amazed, and cut off her head. The ſpectators bewayled her with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie tears: and manie at that ſame houre believed, and were caſten inte deepe Dungeons.</p>
                     <p>Another Virgine called <hi>Maxima,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">MAXIMA</note> being ſo horriblie tormented by <hi>Saſon</hi> prince of <hi>Vandals,</hi> and yet could not be vrged to forſake CHRIST, hee let her goe free. But manie others which were in Priſon, hee baniſhed into the Yle of <hi>Capſur,</hi> vnder the king of <hi>Mores:</hi> where they preached the Goſpell: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards were eaten with wilde people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maximine</hi> was a cruell Perſecuter of the Chriſtians: and tooke his chiefe pleaſure in devyſing new tormenting Inſtruments, to perplexe them with a languiſhing death. But he was not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to invent their Sorrow, than they were earneſtlie readie to ſuffer all that hee could imagine. But eſpeciallie the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14376:49"/> Women: Amongſt whom were <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">SO PHRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA. DORO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THEA.</note> and <hi>Sophronia;</hi> who choſe farre ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to drinke out the verie dreggs of the Cup of Death, than anie wayes to ſhrinke a whit from the Confeſſion of the true Fayth.</p>
                     <p>And the ſame GOD which ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened theſe Women in all kynde of Martyrdome, (yea, and in the pangues of Death) for His Names ſake, wroght alſo in the heart of this Tyrant, that he was overcome with the conſtant ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe in the Religion of theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: In ſo much, that hee cauſed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh an Edict, and proclaymed through all his Empyre, That none ſhould mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them in anie thing, vpon poene of Death.</p>
                     <p>Thus wee clearlie beholde the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie great loving Mercies of our GOD towards Woman Sexe: who hath ſtil ſo mightily aſſiſted them even with His Divine Strength, to ſuffer all whatſoever could bee layd vpon them, without ſhrinking, vnto the laſt period of Breath: no, not in Death it ſelfe. And thus wee proceede.</p>
                     <p>The Church Hiſtorie maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14376:50"/> of an ancient Virgine of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> whom the perſecutioner tooke, and drew out all her teeth, and then <note place="margin">A VIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GINE MARTYR</note> her tongue alſo; and brought her to the fire, to bee burnt quicke. And when they intreated her, yet to forſake CHRIST, ſhee reſolutelie leaped into the fire, and was burnt to powder, about the yeare of our LORD 251.</p>
                     <p>About which tyme alſo was a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Woman, called <hi>Coïnth,</hi> vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie,
<note place="margin">COÏNTH</note> and filthilie drawne, at a horſe tayle, thorow all the nookes of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And yet continuing ſteadfaſt, they rent her in pieces, with vglie diſguyſed perſons, lyke Devils, and Death himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Socrates</hi> telleth, that a Temple was <note place="margin">SOCRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES LIB. 6. CAP.
33.</note> erected in the towne of <hi>Edeſſe,</hi> in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia,</hi> to the honour of GOD, and the Apoſtle Sainct <hi>Thomas;</hi> in the which the Chriſtians vſed to aſſemble, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their ſacrifices, of prayer, prayſe, and thankſgiving, vnto the GOD of Heaven. Which when the Emperour <hi>Valens</hi> vnderſtood, who was an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enemie to the ſervants of the true God, and an accurſed perſuer of all ſuch as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14376:50"/> profeſſed the Name of IESUS, hee was wrathfull towards <hi>Modeſtus</hi> the chiefe Captayne; ſent for him, and reproved him verie ſharplie, for ſuffering the Chriſtians, contrarie his will, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: And gaue him charge, on payne of Death, and his whole poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that the next tyme that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians coveaned in Saynct
<hi>Thomas</hi> Church, hee ſhould murder them all, both young, and olde. Now this
<hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtus,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">MODE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STUS.</note> the chiefe Captayne, was a good Man, and ſent private advertiſement to the Chriſtians, that vpon their next awonted day of aſſemblie in Sainct <hi>Thomas</hi> Church, none ſhould bee found there, who loved his lyfe. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, vpon their vſuall day, they came to the Church in great numbers, to ſay their Prayers: and <hi>Modeſtus,</hi> making a ſhow to ſatisfie the Emperours evill purpoſe, was marching thitherwards, with a band of armed ſouldiours: and ſeeing a Chriſtian Woman, with a chylde in her armes, running towards the Church, hee called her, ſaying; Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie Woman that thou art, whither art thou going? Shee anſwered, To
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14376:51"/> the Temple of Saynct <hi>Thomas.</hi> Haſt thou not heard tell, quoth hee, that the Emperour hath commanded mee to ſlay all that are in the Temple to day? Yes, ſhee ſayde, and therefore I haſte mee thitherwardes, with my chylde, that wee may die with the reſt of our Brethren, and Siſters.</p>
                     <p>This chiefe Captayne ſeeing the Woman ſo reſolutelie bent, with her little one, to ſuffer for the Name of CHRIST, returned with his ſouldiors, to the Emperour, tolde him what the Woman had ſayde, and deſired, rather to ſuffer Martyrdome himſelfe with the Chriſtians, than to worke anie thing agaynſt them. Whereby the Emperour was put from his helliſh purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Saleucia</hi> had a Siſter, called <hi>Tharbua;</hi> who becauſe ſhe <note place="margin">THAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BUA.</note> would not renounce the fayth of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS, was bound to a poſt, and her Mayde to another, and were cut in twayne, in the middle, with a Saw, and never ſhrunke for the matter.</p>
                     <p>And vnder the Reygne of Emperour <hi>Adrian,</hi> there was an holie, &amp; wyſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14376:51"/> called <hi>Sophia,</hi> who had three daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <note place="margin">SOPHI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> which ſhee ſaw cruellie executed, for the Name of IESUS; ſhee ſtanding by, and giving them cowrage, to the laſt gaſpe. And beeing dead, ſhee bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them, with her owne handes, without the Citie of <hi>Rome;</hi> giving great prayſe vnto GOD, glorie, and thanks, who had made her ſo happie a Woman, that the fruit of her Wombe was ſo reſpected of the LORD, as to account them worthie, to bee of the number of thoſe that ſuffered for the Name, and Glorie of the LORD IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS.</p>
                     <p>But, ſeeing it is not poſſible for me, nor none elſe to regiſtrate all the ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt &amp; conſtant Women, in Godlineſſe, Vertue, Wiſdome, Learning, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Cowrage, Chaſtitie, and manie other excellent perfections: (for, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſuch a taske would fill the world full of Bookes, and yet never bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) Therefore, at this tyme, I thinke to conclude this my little Eſſay, (to the Honour of GOD, and good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,) with the eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie of the <hi>Maccabees.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14376:52"/> Wee reade, that two Women were brought in, and accuſed, for not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the manners of the Gentiles; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, according to the Law of GOD, they had circumciſed their little ones; which, hanging on their Mothers breaſts, they hurried them, ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, round about the Citie; and then, both Women, and Infants, were throwne headlongs downe from the Wall.</p>
                     <p>Agayne, a Mother, with her ſeaven Sonnes, were cruellie, and vnhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, tortured, and alſo put to Death, becauſe they would not forſake the Law of GOD, and their fathers. And this part of Scripture teſtifieth, That the Woman was marvelous aboue all, and worthie of honourable memorie, for when ſhee ſaw her ſeaven Sonnes ſlayne, within one dayes ſpace, ſhee bare it with a good cowrage, becauſe of the hope which ſhee had in the LORD.</p>
                     <p>But, to vnderſtand this Hiſtorie the better, I pray you reade the ſeaventh Chapter of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees,</hi> where it is alreadie moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14376:52"/> ſet downe, even by the Spirit of GOD: vnto whom I conſecrate my ſelfe for ever, &amp; recommend all good Women; vnto whom, next vnto God, I dedicate my mynde, ſince my might is not able to performe what my Muſe would fayne amount vnto: And to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my brevitie, I muſt conclude with Maſter Taylor, That</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The ſhorteſt Writ, the greateſt Wit affordes:</l>
                           <l>And greateſt Wit, conſiſts in feweſt wordes.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poems">
                  <head>A falſe ECHO, truelie anſwered.</head>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>The firſt Summonds,</head>
                     <l>Come ECHO, I doe thee ſummon,</l>
                     <l>Tell mee truelie, What is a Woman?</l>
                     <lg>
                        <head>ECHO.</head>
                        <l>If worne, ſhee is a Feather:</l>
                        <l>If wooed, ſhee's froſtie weather.</l>
                        <l>If wonne, the wind's not ſlighter:</l>
                        <l>If vexed, the Moone's not lighter:</l>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:14376:53"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:14376:53"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14376:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:14376:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14376:55"/>
                        <l>If lyen withall, ſhee's Apiſh:</l>
                        <l>If lyen with none, ſhee's ſnappiſh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ECHO thus replyed,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But yet mee thought it lyed.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>The ſecond Summonds.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come ECHO, I thee Summon,</l>
                        <l>Tell me once more, What's a Woman?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>ECHO.</head>
                        <l>If fayre, ſhee's coy in courting:</l>
                        <l>If wittie, looſe in ſporting:</l>
                        <l>If readie, ſhee is loathing:</l>
                        <l>If naked, ſhee is nothing:</l>
                        <l>If well belov'd, ſhee ſcornes thee:</l>
                        <l>If not belov'd, ſhee hornes thee:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>The Anſwere.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And, for all good Womens ſake,</l>
                        <l>This Replye now doe I make;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If worne, ſhee's a jewell:</l>
                        <l>If wooed, ſhee is not cruell:</l>
                        <l>If wonne; the Rock's not ſurer:</l>
                        <l>If weyghed, the Golde's not purer:</l>
                        <l>If lyen withall, Delicious:</l>
                        <l>If lyen with none, not vicious.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Falſe ECHO, goe, you lye,</l>
                        <l>For this is a Woman truely.</l>
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:14376:55"/>
                        <l>And for your ſecond Summon,</l>
                        <l>I anſwere for a Woman.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If fayre, ſhee's heavenlie Treaſure:</l>
                        <l>If wittie, ſhee's all Pleaſure:</l>
                        <l>If readie, farre from Vaynties:</l>
                        <l>If naked, ſhee is Daynties:</l>
                        <l>If well belov'd, ſhee feares not:</l>
                        <l>If not belov'd, ſhee cares not:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Falſe ECHO, goe, you lye,</l>
                        <l>For this is a Woman truely.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <l>BLeſt bee the Heavenlie Powers, which brought to light</l>
                     <l>This precious jemme call'd <hi>WOMAN,</hi> Man's Delight:</l>
                     <l>This Free-borne Princeſſe, Casket full of Treaſure:</l>
                     <l>This ſolid Author of Man's wiſhed Pleaſure.</l>
                     <l>This harmleſſe ſpotleſſe Saynct, not knowing evill,</l>
                     <l>A Goddeſſe, though prowde man would proue a Devill.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:14376:56"/> Why? Shee's a Worke ſo purelie wrought, that Nature</l>
                     <l>Knew not whether 'twas more adorn'd with Feature,</l>
                     <l>Or with chaſte Honeſtie. And this was Shee,</l>
                     <l>Fruit of whoſe wombe fred Man from Miſerie.</l>
                     <l>For which Shee's bleſt, that Her Sexe Faults ſhall fall.</l>
                     <l>From ſmall, to leſſe; from leſſe, to none at all.</l>
                     <l>And therefore thus wee may defyne a <hi>WOMAN;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shee's louelie, faythfull, harmleſſe, falſe to no man.</l>
                     <l>Altho that Man, as an incarnate Devill,</l>
                     <l>Of Her whom GOD made good, would fayne make evill.</l>
                     <l>And if ſweete Womens loue doe not Men cheriſh,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that contemne their Sexe, with ſhame ſhall periſh.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="epilogue">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:14376:56"/>
                  <head>Epilogue.</head>
                  <p>THus to avoyde the imputation of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude,</hi> which was holden for ſo haynous an Offence even amongſt the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that <hi>Periander</hi> of <hi>Corinth</hi> made a Law, that whoſoever was found vnthankefull, having receaved anie Gift, ſhould bee put to death: Therefore,</p>
                  <l>With lowlie Heart, and eke with thankfull Mynde,</l>
                  <l>I ſende my Labours to Good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-kynde.</l>
                  <p>Indeede, what the loftineſſe of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requyreth, I confeſſe, I haue not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned vnto: Yet haue I beſtowed ſuch willing paynes, as I was able to vndergoe: but nowayes heerein can I ſatisfie my ſelfe to doe them Good. Nevertheleſſe, I ſhall holde my ſelfe recompenſed to the full, if by anie willingneſſe I may reſerue the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of Honourable Women, in relating the Trueth in Honeſtie and Wiſedome: Deſiring no more, but to find a place, for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14376:57"/> a tyme, amongſt the pettie Writers of great matters: thinking my paynes ever well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, if once well accepted: no wayes taking vpon mee to Inſtruct; but onelie to Remember.</p>
                  <p>Surelie, if the poore <hi>Perſians</hi> water in a potſheard, was acceptable to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; and, an apple, from a poore <hi>Peſſant,</hi> was receaved by <hi>Artaxerxes;</hi> a great <note place="margin">ARTAX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ERXES. ALEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDER.</note> Prince: if <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke water cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſlie from a common Souldiours Helmet; and our Saviour crowned the Widow, with everlaſting prayſe, for two mytes caſten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Treaſurie: Then am I aſſured, that your generous diſpoſitions will ſparinglie cenſure, and courteouſlie receaue theſe my poore Endeavours. Which howſoever they be, they be yours, &amp; ſo am I: Ever wiſhing, To buy the <hi>ABATEMENT</hi> of mine owne <hi>HONOUR,</hi> with the ritch pryce of <hi>WO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANS TRUE GLORIE:</hi> Concluding with Maſter <hi>GIBSON,</hi> That</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It is no BOUNTIE which doth flow from STORE.</l>
                        <l>Who giues his Heart, what Gift can hee giuE moRe?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:14376:57"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE Duetie of Husbands: Drawne out of MASTER CARTER his Booke of</hi> Chriſtian Common-Wealth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EPHES.</hi> 5. 33.</p>
                  <p>Let everie one of you ſo loue his Wyfe, even as himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PROV.</hi> 31. 11. 12.</p>
                  <p>The Heart of Her Huſband doeth ſafelie trust in Her: <hi>For</hi> Shee will doe him good, and not evill, all the dayes of his lyfe.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="epigraph">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:14376:58"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO</hi> All Good Husbands.</head>
                  <l>Good Husbands all, receaue in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full part,</l>
                  <l>This Sacrifice, (which may my Will approue:)</l>
                  <l>Upon the Altar of a faythfull Heart,</l>
                  <l>Conſumed in the Flames of Zeale an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Loue.</l>
                  <l>Let Honourable Woman liue for ever,</l>
                  <l>In all that Arte, that Tyme, that Fame can giue <hi>hER.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:14376:58"/>
                  <head>The Introduction.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Atient <hi>IOB</hi> ſaying, that the whole lyfe of Man was nothing elſe, but a tyme of Temptations, ſpake moſt fearfullie, and yet moſt truelie: for wee are tempted in our olde Age; and in our Cradle wee are not free. If anie evill bee ſet before vs, wee are eaſilie provoked vnto it. If wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with <hi>Adam,</hi> in Paradiſe, there may bee <hi>Death</hi> in that: And, if wee want, with our Saviour, in the Wilderneſſe, there are Temptations in that alſo: So ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile is Satan, and ſo envyous is our Enemie, to ſerue himſelfe, even vpon all occaſions.</p>
                  <p>In the former age of the World, hee wrought, and prevayled with Men, by bringing in Errours of Mynde, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Devils, to ſeduce the Church: But now the cleare light of the Goſpell bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come in, and Knowledge abounding, hee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14376:59"/> laboureth to bring in Errour of lyfe, and depravitie of Converſation; for that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding men know their Maſters will, yet they performe it not, that all meanes poſſible ought to bee vſed, for the Reformation of theſe ſo notorious and knowne Evills: yea, everie man to put a hand to this worke: amongſt the number of which, I haue brought foorth this my poore Talent, to the fartherance thereof: that wee married Men may ſtryue yet with our Arch-enemie; and, through the aſſiſtance of GOD'S Spirit, giue him the foyle; even by ſhowing our vpright duetie towardes our Wyues, and our wyues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, in the true loue and feare of GOD.</p>
                  <p>As for theſe contentious objectours, and barkers agaynſt the Moone, I weygh not. Shepheardes, Cow-heardes, and Clownes, haue writen good thinges, yea, Divyne matters; Why, then, may not I ſhow my good will? deſiring no other Reward, nor Thankes for my paynes, but onlie good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance: And ſo I goe forwardes to thE WoRke.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="husbands' duty" type="text">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:14376:59"/>
                  <head>The Duetie of <hi>Huſbands.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>THE FIRST CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Duetie of Husbands, is ſayd to bee the firſt Degree which GOD gaue vnto Man after his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for, when GOD had made Man the Ruler of the whole Earth, and gaue him dominion over all the creatures therein; yet, vntill Hee gaue vnto him a Wyfe, hee had no true contentment in all the reſt. For everie creature had ſolace, in their kynde except Man: but ſo was it not with Man, till he had a Wyfe. But then finding her a fit Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to aſſociate himſelfe withall, with her hee ſetled his Content.</p>
                     <p>And this did GOD for Man in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14376:60"/> tyme of his innocencie; giving vs thereby this inſtruction, That wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ought to liue ſo vprightlie, holilie, louelie, &amp; purelie in the ſtate of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, that we ſinne not againſt GOD, nor agaynſt one another.</p>
                     <p>Now, heere is one ſpeciall thing to bee noted; That GOD gaue vnto Man but one Wyfe; and not two, or three, or manie; altho Hee could haue given him moe, if hee had knowne it meete ſo to bee. But the Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">MALAC. 2.</note> telleth vs why GOD gaue him but one: <hi>Becauſe,</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>Hee ſought a Godlie Seede.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See, then, GOD rejecteth the ſeede of Baſtardie, begotten in filthie luſtfull fornication, and abominable Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Hee chooſeth none of theſe: it is the ſeed of lawfull Wedlocke, whereof Hee maketh His choyſe, to inherite His Kingdome, and reygne in Glorie, with His beloved Sonne.</p>
                     <p>And whence proceeded this breach, of GOD'S commandement at the firſt? Came it not from that wicked blood of <hi>Caine?</hi> Was not <hi>Lamech,</hi> that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, lyke his father, the firſt author
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14376:60"/> thereof? Yea, hee was ſo, For wee ſee plainlie, that at the firſt GOD or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned it not ſo to bee: and what Hee firſt ordayned, Hee ſtill confirmeth. For when hee drowned the whole <note place="margin">GEN. 4.</note> World, yet Hee preſerved vnto <hi>Noah</hi> but one Woman, and that his owne wyfe: thereby teaching vnto Man, That he ought to keepe himſelfe vnto his owne wyfe onlie. And when the LORD gaue His Lawes, vnto His own choſen People, written even with His owne Hand, Hee then ſayeth; <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neyghbours</hi>
                        <note place="margin">EXOD. 20.</note> 
                        <hi>Wyfe,</hi> ſpeaking in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: ſo that by Him wee finde no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a plurall.</p>
                     <p>But if anie will object, and ſay, That the Saynctes and Servantes of GOD, as <hi>Abraham, Jaacob, David, Salomon,</hi> and others, haue not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this rule; but haue had dyverſe wyues; and beeing the beloved and choſen of GOD, therefore they could not erre in theſe thinges.</p>
                     <p>To this I anſwere; It pleaſed GOD to permit his Servants to doe manie thinges, which Hee commanded not:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14376:61"/> Hee ſuffered <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſay, that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> his wyfe, was his ſiſter, <hi>Joſeph</hi> to <note place="margin">GEN. 11. GEN. 44.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. SAM. 11</note> ſweare by the lyfe of
<hi>Pharaoh, David</hi> to commit Adulterie, and Murder, and manie other the lyke: and yet, wee know, that all theſe thinges were directlie contrarie to the will of God. And <hi>Salomon</hi> had manie wyues, indeed, <note place="margin">1. KINGS 11.</note> but they drew him to Idolatrie.</p>
                     <p>Wee reade, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuffered the People of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> to giue their Wyues <note place="margin">DEVT. 24.</note> a bill of Divorcement, and ſo to put them away. But our bleſſed Saviour telleth the <hi>Jewes, That it was for the hardneſſe of their hearts;</hi> And, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent farder evills, that <hi>Moſes</hi> permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to bee ſo: and, <hi>That from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">MATTH. 10.</note> 
                        <hi>it was not ſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, to come to our matter agayne; let vs ſee from whence this wyfe came, which GOD hath given vnto Man; that ſo of him ſhee may accordinglie bee reguarded, as indeede ſhee ſhould.</p>
                     <p>Wee finde it to bee moſt true, That of Mans owne ſelfe, GOD made him this Companion and Wyfe: And that not from the hand of Man neyther, leſt ſhee ſhould clayme to rule, where
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14376:61"/> her power conſiſteth not; nor of the foot, leſt ſhee ſhould bee diſdayned, &amp; deſpyſed, of her Husband: but from the verie bodie is ſhee taken. Nay, it is not anough for thee to ſpare of thyne owne fleſh, for to make thee a wyfe of; but thou muſt ſpare a bone alſo, if thou wilt haue a fit Companion for thee.</p>
                     <p>Then, O Man, bee thankfull for ſo ritch a Iewell; ritch, and deare, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, beeing ſo neare vnto thee, and that from the onlie Hand of the Great and Almightie GOD. Surelie it muſt needes be exceeding good which Hee maketh, and of a great value which hee vouchſafeth to giue. Wee haue an olde Proverbe, <hi>That it is a ſweete Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, that is cut out of the owne fleſh.</hi> Then, it muſt needes bee both ſweete and deare, which is both of thyne owne fleſh and bone. Therefore, let vs bee wyſe in vſing this jewell as we ought; leſt wee bee found vnworthie of her, by Him that gaue her vnto vs, and then too late wee lament our incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable loſſe.</p>
                     <p>Then, who ſo would keepe a good Wyfe, let him keepe her in the place
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14376:62"/> from whence ſhe came; that is, from neare thyne heart, O Man: therefore lay her there agayne: let her not ſtray from thence: yea, locke her in there, with the Key of good Diſcretion: and ſo ſhalt thou be ſure, to find a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Treaſure of Her in thy need.</p>
                     <p>But if anie would ſay, Where is the Wyfe that deſerveth ſuch a place? For there are manie ſuch lewde and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">ECCLUS. 26.</note> wyues, that their husbandes are happieſt when they are fardeſt from them. I anſwere ſuch (to their owne ſhame) with theſe wordes of SALO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON, That <hi>a vertuous and good woman ſhall bee given vnto him that feareth the LORD:</hi> and <hi>a wicked woman is given as a reward vnto a wicked man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And therefore, he that would haue a good wyfe, let him earneſtlie ſtryue to feare the LORD, that hee may bee a good husband; and ſo (of the free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of GOD) obtayne ſuch a Bleſſing as is a good wyſe: whoſe commendations wyſe <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe could no wayes ſufficientlie expreſſe: and farre leſſe ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Raban:</hi> but let her owne workes giue her her due prayſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:14376:62"/>
                     <head>THE SECOND CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>NOw, ſince Man hath receaved ſo precious a jewell, and deare Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, as is WOMAN, let vs juſtlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Dueties which hee is bound vnto, firſt to wardes GOD, for ſuch an incomparable Bleſſing, and then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Her.</p>
                     <p>And if in this caſe wee ſearch the whole Booke of GOD thorow, wee ſhall finde the effect and ende thereof, to be wholie and onlie Loue. Saynct <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, That <hi>men ought to loue their wyues, as their owne bodies.</hi> And hee ſhoweth the reaſon why: <hi>For,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>no man ever yet hated his owne fleſh, but</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">EPHES. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>nowriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as Chriſt doeth His Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus did the Saynctes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantes of GOD loue their wyues in tymes paſt:
<hi>Abraham</hi> loved <hi>Sara</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirelie, <note place="margin">GEN. 23 and 26.</note> and ſo did <hi>Iſaac</hi> loue <hi>Rebecca.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This hath that great Prophet and Servant of GOD, <hi>Moſes,</hi> worthilie expreſſed, thereby to ſhow vnto men, That it is not anough for them to liue peaceablie and quyetlie with their
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14376:63"/> Wyues; but they muſt liue lovinglie with them alſo.</p>
                     <p>Thus did <hi>Jaakob</hi> loue his wyfe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſervice vnto his vncle <hi>Laban,</hi> not onlie ſeaven years, but fourteen: to the <note place="margin">GEN. 28.</note> ende hee might enjoy her thereafter.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Helkana</hi> loved <hi>Hanna</hi> his wyfe <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. SAM. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>UD. 14. TOB. 6.</note> moſt dearlie: and ſo did <hi>Samſon,</hi> and both olde and young
<hi>Tobias,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie others.</p>
                     <p>And, as wee haue ſayde before, this Loue muſt not bee ordinarie, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, towardes our wyues: and muſt imitate that Great Loue which CHRIST ſhowed vnto His Church, who gaue Himſelfe for it. Yet this is a great myſterie. For we are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to follow CHRIST punctuallie &amp; perfectlie, but in imitation, as farre as it ſhall pleaſe Him to inable vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: That is, Wee muſt protect our Wyues, and defend them in all perils &amp; dangers: wee muſt governe them in wiſdome, according to the Rule of GOD'S Word, both by continuall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from thence, &amp; by our owne louelie, wyſe, and gentle behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: and we muſt be laborious
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14376:63"/> &amp; carefull in our Callings, in the feare of GOD; ſo that wee may provyde all thinges neceſſarie for their mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. For ſo doeth CHRIST for His Church: He is ſtill defending and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyding for her. <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſayth He, bleſſed for ever) <hi>ſhall a man leaue father and mother, and cleane vnto his wyfe; and</hi>
                        <note place="margin">MATTH 19. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>they twaine ſhall bee one fleſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Saynct <hi>Peter,</hi> beeing himſelfe a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Man, giveth manie notable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions lyke theſe: who ſpeaking by the Spirit of GOD, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hee had of Marriage, impoſeth this duetie vnto Men; <hi>Yee Huſbands,</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>dwell with your Wyues, as men of Knowledge; giving honour vnto the woman, as vnto the weaker veſſell; even as</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. PET. 3</note> 
                        <hi>they which are heyres together of the grace of lyfe; that your Prayers bee not interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> And the wyſe man giveth this counſell, <hi>Not to depart from a diſcreet and good Woman, which is fallen vnto thee for thy portion in the feare of the LORD. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe thy ſelfe to liue joyfullie with thy wyfe, all the dayes of thy lyfe; for that is thy Portion in this lyfe of all thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ECCLES 7.</note> 
                        <hi>and travell that thou takeſt vnder the Sunne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:14376:64"/> And, our bleſſed Saviour CHRIST Himſelfe, confirming on earth, what His Father had done in Paradiſe, vouchſafed to grace a nuptiall feaſt, with His bleſſed preſence. And to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt His Loue the more which Hee bore to the holy Union then there knit betwixt the Man and his Wyfe, Hee expreſſed His Glorie and Power, in ſhowing His firſt miracle at this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and that of joy; by turning wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into wyne, even to comfort and
<note place="margin">IOHN 2.</note> glad their hearts withall.</p>
                     <p>But now ſeeing wee haue proven, out of GOD'S word, that the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall duetie of Husbandes towards thier Wyues, is <hi>Loue,</hi> let vs looke into the glaſſe of our tymes, and ſee how the duetie of <hi>Loue</hi> is performed. But I feare, that amongſt an hundreth wee ſhall ſcarcelie finde one that ſtryveth to performe this duetie of <hi>Loue</hi> as hee ought. For ſee wee not daylie rather the contrarie by many? Men conſume the eſtates which they haue gotten by their wyues, thorow their owne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lyues; ſome by ſloathfull ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſome by gayming, ſome by
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14376:64"/> drunkenneſſe, ſome by whoring, and manie other ſorts of damnable living. And thus are good Women brought to Beggerie, by lewde, ſhameleſſe, and godleſſe Husbands, who haue altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſaken the LORD, ſhowing neyther Loue nor Duetie to their Wyues, who are their owne verie fleſh, blood, and bones.</p>
                     <p>Other Husbandes agayne, to ſhow their authoritie, forſooth, will holde their wyues in ſuch ſubjection, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, that no ſervand nor ſlaue could abyde the lyke; beeing even a verie <hi>Naball</hi> vnto them, in churliſhneſſe of ſpeach, and crabbedneſſe of Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Where is wiſdome in ſuch Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, who are commanded to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne their Wyues in loue, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Knowledge?</p>
                     <p>Other fellow-impudents with theſe, will not labour, nor care for nothing; but put the poore woman to ſhift for all. Or, if perhaps hee get ſomething abroad, yet ſhee is ſure not to bee the better thereof: it muſt bee ſpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee come home, or elſe hidden from her preſence. What ſhall we ſay of ſuch <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                           <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:14376:65"/> veth GOD, and yet loveth not his wyfe, I ſay hee is a lyar in graine.</p>
                     <p>But, when I haue all done, and ſayd what I can, yet I muſt leaue men to the conſideration of what is written, and wiſh, and intreate them, to bee wyſe, and ſubmit themſelues vnto the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of the Word of GOD: that ſo they may liue quyetlie, and loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with their Wyues: and not onlie ſo, but joyfullie alſo, (as the wyſe man ſayeth) <hi>for, ſurelie, hee hath obtayned a good portion, who hath a wyfe that hee can liue joyfullie with.</hi> For, what if a Man doe abound in wealth, ſo that hee can giue vnto himſelfe as much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as
<hi>Salomon</hi> poſſeſſed, <hi>even what his heart can deſire?</hi> yet, if hee liue not peaceablie at home, and in loue with his wyfe, all is but an heavie and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull burden vnto him. But the poore man, having little, and yet living friendlie, lovinglie, and joyfullie, with his wyfe, hath ten thouſand tymes more than the rich co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious wretch; his heart beeing filled with content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the LORD, and the other his heart full of wretchedneſſe, and the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14376:65"/> ſting of an evill conſcience.</p>
                     <p>Wee haue an olde Proverbe, That <hi>in Loue is no lacke.</hi> For, where <hi>Loue</hi> is vnited with the feare of GOD, in the hearts of Man and Wyfe, they will, lyke yoak-fellowes, draw together the right way, lyke the two milke-kyne, which brought the Arke of GOD, in the new Cart, from the land of the <hi>Philiſtimes:</hi> Yea, they will plow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſow together: and there is no doubt, but through the bleſſing of Him who governeth them, they ſhall receaue a plentifull harveſt together.</p>
                     <p>Thus, wee haue found, that the principall duetie of the Husband to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his Wyfe, is
<hi>Loue:</hi> which due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is now-a-dayes neglected, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and even deſpyſed of manie, who haue turned aſide, and forſaken the way of the LORD, as appeareth by the evills and miſchiefes which daylie aryſe betwixt Man and Wyfe. And, therefore, having deſcryed a mayne defect in Husbands, the which wee may not paſſe over, becauſe it is the greateſt breach of
<hi>Loue</hi> that may bee,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14376:66"/> wee ſhall ſpeake ſomething thereof
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the next Chapter, GOD permmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>THE FOURTH CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>THis duetie of the Husband vnto the Wyfe, beeing whollie inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Bands of
<hi>Loue,</hi> it ſtreatcheth it ſelfe farder, into manie branches. For wee finde alſo by the Word of GOD, that the Husband muſt dwell with his Wyfe, according to Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. So wee ſee heere, that it is not lawfull for the Husband to forſake his Wyfe: but, howſoever, whether it bee in weale or woe, in ritches or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie, yet hee muſt abide, and dwell with her ſtill, except it bee onlie for the fact of Adulterie; and for no other cauſe may a Man forſake his Wyfe, nor a Wyfe her Husband.</p>
                     <p>Indeede the wyſe man ſayeth, <hi>Giue mee anie plague, but the plague of the tongue.</hi> And, it may bee, ſome wyues haue this imperfection; but, conſider rightlie, if thou thy ſelfe bee not the vrgent cauſe thereof. Howſoever, it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14376:66"/> is not a cauſe ſufficient to forſake her, as teſtifieth our Saviour, who vtterlie <note place="margin">MATTH. 19.</note> forbiddeth to ſeparate thoſe whom GOD hath joyned together, Adulterie onlie beeing accepted.</p>
                     <p>But the verie fyre-brandes of Hell, even the wicked, and abominable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, of our tyme, neyther reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Word of GOD, nor yeelding any obedience to His co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, or fearing the juſtice of His vengeance, to come for their ſtiff-neckedneſſe, will, notwithſtanding, lyke the Swyne poſſeſſed by the Devill, runne, violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to their Deſtruction. But Saynct <hi>Paull</hi> telleth playnlie, that <hi>neyther For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, Adulterers, Wantons, or ſuch</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. COR. 6</note> 
                        <hi>lyke, ſhall inherite the Kingdome of GOD.</hi> Whither they ſhall goe, then, let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good Chriſtian tremble to thinke of. For theſe men, not regarding any thing, will haue a Wyfe heere, and another there; one in this Countrey, and another elſe-where: or if they be no Travellers, will thinke no ſhame to keepe a whore vnder his wyues noſe: and ſhee dare not finde fault with it, but may know, and dare not know.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14376:67"/> Yea, manie not yet contented heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but proceed farder: for all theſe damnable abuſes <hi>ſeeme ſweet to a whore-monger,</hi> ſayeth the wyſe man: <hi>neyther will hee leaue off, till hee periſh.</hi> But <note place="margin">ECCLES. 23</note> hearken what hee ſayeth farder; to wit, <hi>that ſuch a man ſhall be put to ſhame, becauſe hee would not vnderſtand the wayes of the LORD.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What neede wee cite pettie Authors for this Adulterous generation? Let the mouth of GOD take chiefe place, and condemne them, where Hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſslie ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">EXOD. 20.</note> 
                        <hi>thou ſhalt not covet thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wyfe, &amp;c.</hi> And the LORD com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſtricklie, <hi>That there ſhould bee no whore-keepers amongſt His people</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">DEUT. 23.</note> 
                        <hi>Iſraell.</hi> But if all ſuch ſhould be ſwept out of <hi>Britane,</hi> the land would be thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie inhabited. It is counted amongſt young men, <hi>A tricke of youth;</hi> and amongſt other of middle age,
<hi>A veniall ſinne:</hi> yea, the verie aged themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with their Hoarie and Snow-lyke head and beard, their furrowed and wrinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led browes, and their carion face; lyke a dead corpſe, though their abilitie of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14376:67"/> bodie be ſpent, and conſumed, in abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and damnable filthineſſe; yet they will ſpeake now more filthilie, than before they lived laſciviouſlie. Beholde, of all Monſters, <hi>Lust</hi> is the worſt, and that eſpeciallie in olde age, teſtifieth that worthie Clerke <hi>Eraſmus of Rotterdam,</hi> in his Booke of
<hi>Chriſtian</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">ERAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MUS.</note> 
                        <hi>Warrefare, Capitulo</hi> 32. Where he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pithilie exhorteth all ſuch men, to turne backe from ſuch great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſaying, That if it be poſſible for them to get true repentance, it is alſo poſſible for them to bee ſaved.</p>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>But who ſo heere repenteth never,</l>
                           <l>A Reprobate ſhall die for ever.</l>
                        </lg> 
                     </q>
                     <p>So great abhominations were not committed in <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> loe<hi>!</hi> as now reygne amongſt vs, (who were conſumed with fire and brimſton long agoe) and can wee then thinke to eſcape? Alace, no, except wee repent in tyme. And therefore let vs bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the holie PSALMIST, who ſayeth thus: <hi>Oh, conſider this, yee that forget GOD, lest that Hee teare you in</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">PSAL. 50. 22.</note> 
                        <hi>pieces, and there bee none to deliver.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:14376:68"/> Heare yet what Saynct <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth; <hi>Whore-mongers, and Adulterers,</hi> ſayeth <note place="margin">HEB. 13.</note> hee, <hi>GOD will judge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And it is ſayd in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that <hi>they ſhall haue their part in the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone: which is</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">REVEL. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>the ſecond death.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus ſayeth the LORD by His Prophet IEREMIAH: <hi>They aſſemble</hi>
                        <note place="margin">IEREM. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>themſelues, by companies, in the harlots houſes; and ryſe vp in the morning, lyke fed horſes, everie man neyghing after his neyghbours wyfe.</hi> And now mark what followeth: <hi>And ſhall I not viſit for theſe thinges, ſayeth the LORD? Shall not My Soule bee avenged on ſuch a nation as this?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus ſhortlie haue wee procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in opening the breach of Sacred Wedlocke; to the ende, that every one may clearlie ſee, into what dangers thoſe men doe daylie runne, who liue not lovinglie and faythfullie, yea, and joyfullie with their owne Wyues, even as the Word of GOD enjoyneth them to doe. And ſuch a man the wiſe SALO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON proveth to be the moſt fooliſh of all the fooles vnder the Sunne, ſaying;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14376:68"/> That <hi>ſuch a man deſtroyeth his owne ſoule: yea, hee ſhall finde a wound,</hi> ſayeth <note place="margin">PROV. 22.</note> hee, <hi>and diſhonour: and his reproach ſhall never bee put away. And into ſuch a pit ſhall that man fall, with whom the LORD is angrie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>THE FIFT CHAPTER.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapters wee haue ſhowne howe farre manie Husbands come too ſhort of thoſe Due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which by the Word of GOD they are enjoyned to performe vnto their onlie owne Wyues: and the whole cauſe, and chiefe ground whereof, wee ſee to bee, <hi>The want of Loue;</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>of True Loue.</hi> For if in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands were that <hi>True Loue,</hi> which the feare of GOD worketh in the heart of true Chriſtians, it would ſurelie leade them to that
<hi>Knowledge,</hi> wherewith
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14376:69"/> Saynct <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth them to bee <note place="margin">1. PET.
3</note> furniſhed: and the which poynt wee muſt needes handle a little broader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ende this Treatiſe.</p>
                     <p>Now, as wee haue ſhowne before, it is not anough for Husbandes to abyde and dwell with their Wyues: but they muſt dwel with them as men of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding, well expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in the Word of GOD, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whollie to the Rule thereof, and obeying His holie Will and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
                     <p>Heereby commeth that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> which will bring Husbandes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that Duetie which Saynct <hi>Paull</hi> teacheth them towardes their Wyues; to wit, <hi>To loue them,</hi> even
<hi>as CHRIST</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">EPHES. 5</note> 
                        <hi>loved His Congregation:</hi> that is, with an holie, heartie, vnfeygned, and conſtant loue: Which wee can no other wayes attayne vnto, but by the aforeſayde <hi>Godlie Knowledge;</hi> which muſt bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from the Word of GOD, even as a Bee gathereth her honey from the ſweeteſt flowers, and that by continual exercyſe: or elſe bee yee ſure, you ſhall never receaue true Comfort in your Marriages.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="117" facs="tcp:14376:69"/> VVhen <hi>Samuell</hi> had anoynted <hi>Saull</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. SAM.
10.</note> to bee King of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the LORD gaue vnto <hi>Saull</hi> another heart than hee had before; even a heart according to his Calling. So no doubt but thoſe men, whom the LORD calleth vnto that Honourable Eſtate of Marriage, Hee will (and doeth) furniſh them with Giftes according to their places. For indeed it is no ſmall matter, but verie weyghtie, of a
<hi>Novice,</hi> to become the <hi>Father of a Familie,</hi> the governour of a Wyfe, Children, and Servantes, &amp;c. Such a man hath need of another heart than hee had before: even an heart to pray vnto the LORD with <hi>Salomon,</hi> That He would vouchſafe to giue him wiſdome, to goe in and out, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne that Charge with Godlie Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which the GOD of all Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Knowledge hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him.</p>
                     <p>Yet, before wee conclude, let vs alſo conſider the Duetie of FORBEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE, which Husbandes owe vnto their Wyues, as beeing the weaker
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14376:70"/> Veſſels: and Saynct PAVL teacheth vs the reaſon playnlie why:
<hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſayeth hee, <hi>they</hi> (meaning the Wyues) <hi>are Heyres with you of the Grace of Lyfe: Elected by the favour of GOD, in CHRIST JESVS, to that fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Saynctes, wherein your ſelues hope to bee numbered: And, as dearlie beloved of GOD, as your ſelues,</hi> are <hi>bought out of the power of Satan, by the precious Blood of His deare Sonne, as well as you: and Heyres alſo of that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Lyfe which you your ſelues hope to enjoye.</hi> And therefore, if you your ſelues thinke to liue as Sayncts in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heere-after, you muſt firſt liue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as Sayncts heere on Earth.</p>
                     <p>Let theſe thnges, then, bee as a Load-ſtone, to draw Husbandes vnto the performance of all their Dueties towardes their Wyues. For this ſame Apoſtle yeeldeth yet a farther reaſon of the Dueties of LOVE, AMITIE, and FORBEARANCE of Husbandes: to wit, <hi>That your Prayers</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>bee not hindered.</hi> That is: If you would
<pb n="911" facs="tcp:14376:70"/> haue GOD to heare you, when you pray vnto Him, and to grant you the thinges you deſire of Him together, vvhy then, in the Name of GOD, let vs agree together, liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, loue together, and pray together. That ſo our praying together, may receaue comfort together;</p>
                     <closer>And, That THE GOD OF LOVE may bleſſe our Loues togethER. AMEN.</closer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14376:71"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14376:71"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
